<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lexicon_stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::CDRH//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska)//EN" "TEI.dtd" [

]>


<TEI.2 id="treaty.tfl.001">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc.,
                        1851</title>: Revisiting the document found in Kappler's <title>Indian
                        Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title>
                </title>
                <author>Charles D. Bernholz</author>
                <author>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Project Director</resp>
                    <name>Charles D. Bernholz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Project Team</resp>
                    <name>Brian Pytlik Zillig</name>
                    <name>Laura Weakly</name>
                    <name>Karin Dalziel</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska Libraries&amp;#8211;Center for Digital
                    Research in the Humanities</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
                <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
                <idno>treaty.tfl.001</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p><!-- ? (copyright) --></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Original.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-10-20</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Laura Weakly</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial encoding</item>
            </change>

        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front>
            <div1>
                <!--<head rend="center">The <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc.,
                    1851</title>: Revisiting the Document Found in Kappler's <title>Indian Affairs:
                        Laws and Treaties</title></head>


                <milestone unit="crosses"/>-->

                <docAuthor>Charles D. Bernholz, Love Memorial Library, University of Nebraska,
                    Lincoln, NE 68588<ref n="*" target="f01"/>
                </docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities,
                    Love Memorial Library, University of Nebraska, Lincoln, NE 68588<ref n="**"
                        target="f02"/>
                </docAuthor>
                <p/>
            </div1>
            <milestone unit="crosses"/>
            <div1>
                <head>Abstract</head>

                <p>The <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc., 1851</title> was an important
                    transaction formed by the federal government with a number of prominent American
                    Indian tribes of the Great Plains. Its creation and provisions were a
                    demonstration of the growing need for less animosity among the tribes
                    themselves, in part to yield increased security for an ever-growing flow of
                    settlers into the western United States who traversed in the process the tribes'
                    historical lands. However, over the years, a true version of the final
                    transaction &#8212; reflecting intervention by the Senate after the original
                    signing &#8212; has never been published. A proposed correct text is
                    presented here.</p>

            </div1>

            <milestone unit="crosses"/>

        </front>
        <body>
            <div1>



                <epigraph>
                    <quote>"It doubtless is important that all treaties and compacts formed by the
                        United States with other nations, whether civilized or not, should be made
                        with caution and executed with fidelity."</quote>

                    <bibl><author>George Washington</author>, <date>17 September 1789<ref n="1"
                                target="n01"/></date></bibl>
                </epigraph>

                <milestone unit="crosses"/>

                <div2>
                    <p>The formation of treaties with the American Indian tribes in the
                        mid-nineteenth century was firmly placed in the hands of the Indian
                        Department through an appropriations act in 1851: "And be it further
                        enacted, That hereafter all Indian treaties shall be negotiated by such
                        officers and agents of the Indian department as the President of the United
                        States may designate for that purpose" (9 <title>Stat.</title> 574, 586).
                        Such authorization allowed the Commissioners of Indian Affairs to implement
                        across the full expanse of this country, with its mixture of both well- and
                        just-established states and remaining Territories, a broad program to
                        address Indian issues.<ref n="2" target="n02"/> The text of one of the
                        transactions created under this power remains absent from the
                            <title>Statutes at Large</title>: the <title><ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/sio0594.htm">Treaty of Fort Laramie with
                            Sioux, etc., 1851</ref></title> (Kappler, 1904b, pp. 594-596;
                        henceforth <title>Fort Laramie</title>).<ref n="3" target="n03"/> This
                        instrument was only recognized as valid at the turn of the twentieth
                        century, and only then through the actions of the United States Court of
                        Claims in the two Indian depredation cases <title>Moore v. United
                            States</title> (1897) and <title>Roy v. United States and the Ogallala
                            Tribe of Sioux Indians</title> (1910). Even though the pertinent
                            <title>Statutes</title> volume was printed in 1859, a treaty stub
                        &#8212; at 11 <title>Stat.</title> 749 &#8212; states only "This treaty was
                        concluded September 17, 1851. When it was before the Senate for
                        ratification, certain amendments were made which require the assent of the
                        Tribes, parties to it, before it can be considered a complete instrument.
                        This assent of all the Tribes has not been obtained, and, consequently,
                        although Congress appropriates money for the fulfillment of its
                        stipulations, it is not yet in a proper form for publication. This note is
                        added for the purpose of making the references from the Public Laws
                        complete, and as an explanation why the Treaty is not published." Charles J.
                        Kappler's <title>Indian Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title>, first compiled
                        in 1903, has thus served for over a century as the main source for this
                        document.</p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>Charles J. Kappler's <title>Indian Affairs: Laws and
                        Treaties</title></head>
                    <p>During the nineteenth century and as a path other than by referring to the
                            <title>Statutes at Large</title>, four attempts were made to assemble
                        relevant American Indian treaty materials for use by federal agencies. These
                        efforts were <title>Indian Treaties, and Laws and Regulations Relating to
                            Indian Affairs</title> (1826); <title>Treaties Between the United States
                            of America and the Several Indian Tribes, From 1778 to 1837</title>
                        (1837); A <title>Compilation of All the Treaties Between the United States
                            and the Indian Tribes Now in Force as Laws</title> (1873); and
                            <title>Laws of the United States Relating to Indian Affairs</title>
                        (1884).</p>

                    <p>In his "Needed Publications on Indian Matters" subsection of the Annual
                        Report of the Department of the Interior for each of the years 1899, 1900,
                        and 1901, the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, William A. Jones (see Baird,
                        1979), requested a new, up to date collection of these resources. His 1899
                        statement referred to the <title>Treaties Between the United States of
                            America and the Several Indian Tribes</title> assembly created in 1837.
                        In 1900 &#8212; and through reciting this statement again in 1901
                        &#8212; the Commissioner criticized <title>A Compilation of All the
                            Treaties Between the United States and the Indian Tribes Now in Force as
                            Laws</title> from 1873 as "inaccurate" and remarked that "[t]he demand
                        for a publication that shall contain all ratified treaties and agreements
                        made by the United States with the Indian tribes is increasing. It would be
                        in constant use in this office and would be frequently referred to by other
                        Government bureaus and by members of Congress as well as by the public at
                        large" (Annual reports of the Department of the Interior for the fiscal year
                        ended June 30, 1900, 1900, p. 50, and Annual reports of the Department of
                        the Interior for the fiscal year ended June 30, 1901, 1901, pp. 46-47). The
                        Republican Senator from Nevada and Chairman of the Senate Committee on
                        Indian Affairs during the 57th and 58th Congresses, William M. Stewart
                        (1827-1909; R-Nevada),<ref n="4" target="n04"/> brought forward a resolution
                        in May 1902 for such a new publication. He reiterated that "the Secretary of
                        the Interior has recommended for several years a compilation of treaties and
                        Executive orders" (Compilation on Indian Affairs, 1902, p. 5664).</p>

                    <p>Charles J. Kappler (1868-1946), an associate of Stewart's, became Clerk for
                        the Senate Committee on Indian Affairs and brought together these scattered
                        materials into a two-volume set.<ref n="5" target="n05"/> His work
                        &#8212; I<title>ndian Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title> &#8212; was
                        released in 1903 as Senate Document 452 for resources collected through 1
                        December 1902, in two successive <title>United States Congressional Serial
                            Set</title> volumes (Kappler, 1903a and b). The pair was republished
                        with format changes in 1904 (Kappler, 1904a and b), the most important of
                        which was the inclusion in the <title>Treaties</title> volume of the signatures of treaty
                            participants.<ref n="6" target="n06"/> Kappler facilitated Congressional
                        use by providing the final versions of these treaty texts, thereby avoiding
                        all the adjustment mechanics listed in the <title>Statutes at Large</title>,
                        including article deletion, amendment, or parameter changes. His focus on
                        the outcome of each negotiated document is an unequivocal demonstration that
                        Kappler consulted the <title>Statutes at Large</title> to convey the law of
                        the land.</p>

                    <p>The construction of <title>Indian Affairs</title>, and in particular the inclusion of appropriate documents, has been
                        criticized over the years. There was initial concern, during the development
                        of the Senate resolution for the compilation, expressed by Senator Eugene
                        Hale (1836-1918; R-Maine), who referred to previous Congressional subject
                        collection projects that had returned inferior, poorly indexed works
                        (Compilation of Indian Affairs, 1902, p. 5664). To counter this accusation,
                        Senator Stewart provided assurance that this new venture would be better.
                        More recently, Vine Deloria and Raymond J. DeMallie speculated in their
                        Introduction that "[i]n short, after surveying the federal records dealing
                        with Indian treaties, one can only conclude that the list of treaties in
                        Kappler's represents those documents on file at the Bureau of Indian Affairs
                        when Charles Kappler and his clerks began their work. It appears that they
                        simply took several filing drawers filled with documents to the printer"
                        (1999, p. 3).<ref n="7" target="n07"/> This latter conjecture has now been
                        mitigated by a statistical demonstration that Kappler took a far more active
                        role in reliably reproducing the contents of the original treaties (Bernholz
                        and Heidenreich, 2009). There is, however, very little hard data to
                        illuminate the overall atmosphere under which <title>Indian Affairs</title>
                        was developed a century ago.</p>

                    <p>The <title>Guide to the Archives of the Government of the United States in
                            Washington</title>, however, might provide one insight; work on this
                        manual began in January 1903 (Van Tyne and Leland, 1904, p. iii). It
                        contains a description of the Department of the Interior's Office of Indian
                        Affairs at the time of Kappler's work and includes the declaration that
                        "[t]he files of the office do not, so far as is shown by the examination for
                        this report, antedate 1800: papers between 1800 and 1832 are rare; those
                        between 1832 and 1849 are numerous; while those from 1849 to date are
                        practically complete, with the exception of such as have been destroyed as
                        valueless. . ." (p. 146). The <title>Guide</title> further remarked on the holdings at the
                        Department of State, i.e., on those papers kept at the Bureau of Rolls and
                        Library that were divided into chapters enumerated in 1894; Indian treaties
                        were placed in designated chapter K (<title>Bulletin of the Bureau of Rolls
                            and Library</title>, 1895, p. 10). The <title>Guide</title> stated:
                        "Treaties with the Indians have, since 1849, ordinarily been preserved in
                        the Department of the Interior, and many treaties prior to 1849 have been
                        transferred to that department. A large number of treaties, however, made
                        between 1722 and 1868 are on file in the Bureau of Rolls and Library" (Van
                        Tyne and Leland, 1904, p. 13).<ref n="8" target="n08"/> Thus, it appears
                        that a "large number" of critical documents might not have even been at the
                        Office of Indian Affairs at the very moment when Kappler constructed
                            <title>Indian Affairs</title> by allegedly taking, according to Deloria
                        and DeMallie, "several filing drawers filled with documents to the
                        printer."</p>

                    <p>In fact, <title>Indian Affairs</title> was an immediate success. The Annual
                        reports of the Department of the Interior for the fiscal year ended June 30,
                        1903 (1904, pp. 469-474) utilized Kappler's 1903 <title>Treaties</title>
                        volume to identify special cases in a table entitled "Treaties made with
                        Indian tribes in the United States which have been ratified by the Senate."
                        In the courts and with regard to the 1904 version, a 1908 property rights
                        case before the Supreme Court of Oklahoma, <title>Godfrey v. Iowa Land
                            &amp; Trust Co.</title>, cited both volumes as "Kappler's Indian
                        Affairs, Laws, and Treaties [2d Ed.]" (pp. 296-297), a clear manifestation
                        of how promptly this work began to appear in legal opinions. These various
                        decisions made citations to both the <title>Statutes</title> and to Kappler,
                        frequently as mentioned pairs. A search of federal and state cases in
                            <title>LexisNexis Academic</title> exposed an assortment of citation
                        formats, such as "2 C. Kappler" (<title>Merrion v. Jicarilla Apache
                            Tribe</title>, 1982); "2 Kappler's" (<title>Godfrey v. Iowa Land
                            &amp; Trust Co.</title>, 1908); and "2 Kapp" (<title>St. Germaine v.
                            Circuit Court for Vilas County</title>, 1991), and there are
                        supplementary instances of the use of the Roman numeral "II" as the volume
                        number indicator, e.g., "II Kappler" in <title>Navajo Tribe of Indians v.
                            United States</title> (1986).</p>

                    <p>A specific <title>LexisNexis</title> search for citations to <title>Fort
                            Laramie</title> in the <title>Statutes</title> &#8212; i.e., through
                        using 11 <title>Stat.</title> 749 as the search item &#8212; yielded forty-one cases.
                        When this array was coupled with a query for the various ways used to
                        reference Kappler's volumes, seventeen examples emerged, including two
                        judicial proceedings for which Kappler was on brief (<title>Crow Nation or
                            Tribe of Indians of Montana v. United States</title> [1935] and
                            <title>Northwestern Bands of Shoshone Indians v. United States</title>
                        [1945]). These citations to his <title>Treaties</title> volume used "2 C.
                        Kappler," "2 Kappler," "2 Kapp.," "II Kappler," and "Second Kappler."
                        Additional materials from Kappler's fourth volume were presented in four of
                        the cases: the 1935 <title>Crow Nation</title> one ("IV Kapp."); <title>Crow
                            Tribe of Indians v. United States</title> (1960, "IV Kapp.");
                            <title>Sioux Tribe of Indians v. United States</title> (1974, "4
                        Kapp."); and <title>United States v. Finch</title> (1976, "4 Kapp.").</p>

                    <p>Note, however, that such use of the <title>Statutes' Fort Laramie</title>
                        reference is frequently abused. In <title>Sioux Tribe v. United
                            States</title> (1969, p. 372) before the Indian Claims Commission for
                        example, the Commission began its opinion with the territorial boundary
                        specifications for the Sioux, found in Article 5 of Kappler's text (1904b,
                        p. 594). Since none of the treaty's text ever appeared in the <title>Statutes</title>, the
                        Commission was in error to cite the treaty stub at 11 <title>Stat.</title>
                        749 as the source of those land parameters. Similar difficulties arose in
                            <title>Sioux Tribe of Indians v. United States</title> (1969, p. 577)
                        and in <title>Three Affiliated Tribes et al v. United States</title> (1971,
                        p. 193) involving the Arikara, Hidatsa, and Mandan, among others.<ref n="9"
                            target="n09"/></p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>General structure of <title>Fort Laramie</title></head>

                    <p>Boczek (2005) devoted a chapter to "The law of treaties," in which he
                        observed that "a treaty, following its title, consists of a preamble
                        invoking the names of the contracting parties and their motivation for
                        concluding the treaty, followed in numbered articles by substantive
                        (dispositive) provisions, sometimes supplemented by an annex or annexes to
                        the treaty, and then the final provisions, usually including such
                        miscellaneous matters as the opening for signature, ratification, accession,
                        the matter of reservations, declarations and statements, amendments, entry
                        into force, denunciation, depositary, authentic text, and the like" (p.
                        348); his component terminology is employed here. In many instances, the
                            <title>Statutes at Large</title> contain several of these additional
                        mechanisms employed by the Senate during the legislative handling of a
                        specific treaty. Aust (2007, p. 441) has identified "the last, formal part
                        of a treaty beneath which the representatives sign" as the testimonium.</p>

                    <p>This analysis revolves around the components, and their text, of the original
                        transaction from 1851, with special reference to the 1904 version of that
                        event provided by Kappler because the latter has served for so long as the
                        primary source for the proceedings of this event. This attempt is confounded
                        in part because his second edition's version was an extension of the 1903
                        arrangement, the later edition attended now by a testimonium and signature
                        sections that offered additional treaty-specific data. Further, it is clear
                        that the 1904 presentation must have served in turn as the model for his
                        later 1929 one.</p>

                    <p><title>Fort Laramie</title> is in comparison to other Indian treaties a
                        relatively short instrument consisting of a preamble, eight articles, and a
                        testimonium. The preamble, at about 100 words, is longer than every article
                        except numbers 5 and 7, one indication that the text is quite focused and
                        direct. All elements except for Article 5 were populated by a single
                        sentence. Article 5 consisted of eight paragraphs: an introductory one; six
                        geographic definitions of territories for the Sioux; for the Gros Ventre,
                        Mandan, and Arikara; for the Assiniboine; for the Blackfoot; for the Crow;
                        and for the Cheyenne and Arapaho; and a concluding remark employed to
                        protect current land claims by the tribes and their hunting, fishing and
                        transit rights.</p>

                    <p>Sequentially, the individual articles addressed the following issues:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>1) peace among the tribes;</item>
                        <item>2) the right of the federal government to create roads and military
                            posts within the defined areas;</item>
                        <item>3) a federal promise to protect the tribes from depredations;</item>
                        <item>4) a pledge by the tribes that they will desist from
                            depredating;</item>
                        <item>5) the boundary parameters of the respective tribal
                            territories;</item>
                        <item>6) the acknowledgment by the tribes that chiefs have been appointed to
                            represent them in these and in future negotiations;</item>
                        <item>7) the amount and duration specifications of annuities for the tribes;
                            and</item>
                        <item>8) the conditions under which such annuities may be suspended.</item>
                    </list>

                    <p>The annuity controversy &#8212; that has endlessly muddled the
                        understanding of both the treaty's ratification process and the later
                        question of tribal assents &#8212; is centered in Article 7. Here,
                        Kappler provided the Congressional amendment that reduced its projected
                        duration from the original fifty to just ten years, with a potential
                        extension of five additional years, at the discretion of the President. The
                        induced textual change created by this amendment was a legislated action and
                        the proposed document provided here was formed to integrate this later
                        Senate modification into the original 1851 transaction.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>Source paths</head>

                    <p>The abundant use during the last century of Kappler's 1904 collation sets it
                        apart from other providers of recognized American Indian treaty texts. In a
                        sense, the 1903 version was designed to address the Commissioner of Indian
                        Affairs' repeated requests for a collection of all relevant laws and
                        treaties at the beginning of the twentieth century. The 1904
                        version of the <title>Treaties</title> volume, however, added the participants' signature
                        dimension, a personal as well as an historical veneer to the suite of
                        transactions; Kappler said then that the decision to forego the signatures
                        in the earlier edition had been to save space. Thus, in an attempt to
                        understand the origin(s) of the <title>Fort Laramie</title> texts found in
                        Kappler's work (including the 1929 rendition), all post-1851 examples, in
                        combination with the original treaty text itself, must be carefully
                        investigated. None of these various later compilations, though, stated the
                        basis for its account of the 1851 <title>Fort Laramie</title> materials, so
                        questions immediately arise regarding the foundation(s) of Kappler's treaty
                        text.</p>

                    <p>Prospective <title>Fort Laramie</title> text avenues available to Kappler in
                        1902 included, in chronological order:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>The original 1851 parchment treaty. It seems reasonable to assume that
                            federal employees, including Kappler and/or his staff for the collation
                            project, would have had access to this instrument during the preparation
                            of any official compilation in the late nineteenth and early twentieth
                            centuries. In 1960, the National Archives produced a microfilm
                            collection entitled <title>Documents Relating to the Negotiation of
                                Ratified and Unratified Treaties with Various Tribes of Indians,
                                1801-69</title> that contains a series of sixty images of documents
                            pertaining to this specific transaction, including images of the three
                            required assent transactions and of letters from the 1920s that
                            discussed its status. The physical quality of these microfilm texts is
                            poor and so digital images of the original 1851 document, now held at
                            the National Archives, were acquired for this study.</item>
                        <item>Articles of a treaty (1852). This Senate Confidential Executive
                            Document contained the detailed text from the transaction; it most
                            certainly had to be taken from the document created in the field the
                            previous September. The date upon which it was "read the first time,
                            referred to the Committee on Indian Affairs, and ordered to be printed
                            in confidence for the use of the Senate" (p. 1) was exactly five months
                            after the treaty signing date, i.e., on 17 February 1852. The particular
                            spellings for "Yellow Stone river" and "Red Bute" follow those phrases
                            of the physical instrument, and so this replicated text thus served as
                            the surrogate for the original while under ratification consideration by
                            the Senate.</item>
                        <item><title>A Compilation of All the Treaties Between the United States and
                                the Indian Tribes Now in Force as Laws</title> (1873; henceforth,
                            the 1873 <title>Compilation</title>). The <title>Compilation</title> was created
                            through an act of Congress (17 <title>Stat.</title> 579) as part of a
                            general request for a consolidation of laws relating to post-roads and
                            military offenses, and "to prepare a revision of all the Indian treaties
                            now in force as law." A critical aspect of this specific form of
                                <title>Fort Laramie</title> is a declaration preceding the preamble
                            that announced that "The following treaty, though never ratified or
                            printed, is sometimes referred to in appropriations and in other
                            treaties; for instance, treaty with the Sioux, Yankton tribe, proclaimed
                            February 26, 1859." The very presence of this passage is helpful in
                            determining the creation of subsequent versions of this material, even
                            though the ratification statement was incorrect.</item>
                        <item><title>Laws of the United States Relating to Indian Affairs</title>
                            (1884; hereafter, <title>Laws of the United States</title>).
                                <title>Laws</title> relayed the treaty text through an appendix that
                            was declared in the table of contents for a category reserved for
                            "unpublished treaties and agreements" (pp. 317-322). In this example of
                                <title>Fort Laramie</title>, there is a memorandum of "Note.
                            &#8212; This treaty is recognized in the first article of the
                            Yankton Sioux treaty of April 19, 1858 (11 <title>Stats.</title>, p.
                            744)" that parallels the same declaration in the 1873
                                <title>Compilation</title>. Absent the various tribe name spellings,
                            there are many other differences among the signatory names in the assent
                            description of <title>Laws</title> and Kappler's.<ref n="10" target="n10"/> However,
                            the most important aspect linked to this <title>Laws</title> text &#8212; whatever
                            its own source(s) &#8212; is that it must have served as the basis
                            for Kappler's conclusion that the Crow had not confirmed their assent to
                            the annuity duration amendment. This <title>Laws</title> rendition
                            clearly speaks of the <emph>six</emph> "following named tribes, viz,
                            Crows, Assinaboines, Gros Ventres, Mandans, Arickarees, and Sioux of the
                            Missouri" (p. 320), even though the signature section for the assent
                            only contains five headings for the Sioux, Assiniboine, Gros Ventre,
                            Mandan, and Arikara (pp. 321-322).</item>
                    </list>

                    <p>Regardless of it provenance, this treaty has been cited in over three dozen
                        federal and state court cases.<ref n="11" target="n11"/> These uses
                        &#8212; and especially the text variations found in the other
                        compilations &#8212; therefore warrant a reexamination of the
                            <title>Fort Laramie</title> wording. The two pivotal Indian depredation
                        cases &#8212; <title>Moore v. United States</title> (1897) and
                            <title>Roy v. United States and the Ogallala Tribe of Sioux
                            Indians</title> (1910) &#8212; are especially important to a study
                        of <title>Fort Laramie</title> for three reasons. First, they created a platform for the
                        federal Court of Claims to declare that <title>Fort Laramie</title> was a valid
                        transaction, and that it was so for all parties. Second, in this declaration
                        and particularly so for <title>Roy</title>, the Court defined the
                        specifications for a general yet binding treaty, with or without the alleged
                        formality of an attending Presidential proclamation. Third, an examination
                        of the opinions and of the briefs submitted before the Court reveals the
                        various origins for the text of this instrument. These briefs contain far
                        more discussion of the parameters of the treaty, but the timing of these two
                        proceedings &#8212; one before the creation of the two editions of
                        Kappler's <title>Indian Affairs</title>, and one after &#8212; shows the
                        active contemporary use by attorneys of Indian treaty materials, and
                        certainly of the earlier, established compilations for these
                        instruments.</p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>Text analysis</head>
                    <p>Recently, a text analysis tool, TokenX, was used to form a <ref n="http://treatylexicon.unl.edu/">lexicon</ref> for each
                        of the two families of acknowledged American Indian treaty instruments.
                        These were composed of the seven British treaties created during their
                        occupation yet fully recognized by the Department of State, and for the
                        United States, through a combination of the texts of the 366 items in the
                        Oklahoma State University's <ref n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/">
                            Kappler digital collection</ref>) and of the remaining
                        two instruments in the <title>American State Papers</title> (see Bernholz,
                        Pytlik Zillig, and Anderson, 2008). The study's results confirmed a
                        number of errors and discrepancies in the <title>Statutes at Large</title>,
                        in the 1903 and 1904 editions of the <title>Treaties</title> volume, and in
                        the Oklahoma State University digital ensemble. Two word frequency lists
                        &#8212; one sorted alphabetically, the other by count &#8212; aided
                        error identification. The lexicon investigation though, with the presence of
                        errors in <emph>all</emph> sources, generated the subsequent hypothesis that
                        there might be more divergence between those texts found in the
                            <title>Statutes at Large</title> and their corresponding entries in the
                        1904 <title>Indian Affairs</title> treaty volume. In this particular
                        instance and as a special comparable consideration, provenance is an even
                        more important question for <title>Fort Laramie</title> because of its
                        absence from the <title>Statutes at Large</title>.</p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>Treaty text discrepancies</head>
                    <p>Text variability is not a novel question with regard to these critical
                        documents. Edward Channing, in <title>A History of the United States</title>
                        (1921, pp. 68-69), identified four specific sources for negotiations with
                        the tribes: <title>Indian Treaties, and Laws and Regulations Relating to
                            Indian Affairs</title> (1826); <title>Treaties Between the United States
                            of America and the Several Indian Tribes, From 1778 to 1837</title>
                        (1837); the seventh volume of the <title>Statutes at Large</title>, entitled
                            <title>Treaties Between the United States and the Indian Tribes</title>
                        (1846); and Kappler's second <title>Treaties</title> volume (1904b). To
                        these he added Charles C. Royce's <title>Indian Land Cessions in the United
                            States</title> (1899), a significant work that combined a
                        chronologically arranged table of treaty cession transactions with
                        corresponding map(s) to show the extent of the lands transferred through
                        those events.<ref n="12" target="n12"/> Channing remarked that "[t]here are
                        differences in the text of the treaties as printed in these several
                        publications, and some treaties are in one and not in any of the others." As
                        the law of the land, though, it might have been expected that such variation
                        should not have been present, or at least not so prevalent.</p>

                    <p>Francis Paul Prucha, in <title>American Indian Treaties: The History of a
                            Political Anomaly</title>, spoke directly to this question of the
                        reliable publication of these documents (1994, pp. 442-445). In that
                        presentation, Father Prucha identified the assorted laws enacted to direct
                        the State Department and the Department of the Interior to furnish the array
                        of laws and treaties created by the nation. Of special interest was
                            <title>An act to amend the act, entitled "An act to provide for the
                            publication of the laws of the United States, and for other
                            purposes"</title> (1820) that required that Indian treaties "shall be
                        published only in one newspaper, and that to be within the limits of the
                        state, or territory, to which the subject matter of such treaty shall
                        belong" (p. 576). The various compilations in the nineteenth century, such
                        as those identified by Channing in 1921, made it far easier to access these
                        instruments, but these "versions do not display great uniformity in their
                        handling of the treaties or in their concordance with the original
                        manuscript in matters of spelling, capitalization, and punctuation" (Prucha,
                        1994, p. 445). The present study is a reconfirmation of that observation,
                        with the additional stipulation that the actual words have varied since the
                        original document was created.</p>

                    <p>Prucha also remarked that other comparisons have been made of the original
                        texts with those found in the <title>Statutes at Large</title> and in
                        Kappler. Clarence E. Carter, editor of <title>The Territorial Papers of the
                            United States</title>, found a substantial number of punctuation errors
                        but "no important differences in words" for the <title><ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/wya0018.htm">
                            Treaty with the Wyandots,
                        etc., 1789</ref></title>, and there existed as well "more than one hundred changes" of
                        punctuation for the <title><ref 
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/wya0039.htm">
                            Treaty with the Wyandots, etc., 1795</ref></title>, in
                        direct comparisons between the original material and the <title>Statutes at
                            Large</title> texts (Carter, 1934, p. 174 and 525; see Kappler, 1903b,
                        pp. 13-18 and 30-34). In both of these situations, Carter acknowledged that Kappler
                        followed the <title>Statutes</title> account as he created his 1903 <title>Treaties</title>
                        volume (pp. 13-18 and 30-34), thereby incorporating such errors.<ref n="13" target="n13"/></p>

                    <p>It was further observed by Father Prucha that Kappler's 1904
                            <title>Treaties</title> edition "follows a chronological arrangement and
                        relies for its content on the <title>Statutes at Large</title> (although it
                        prints the Fort Laramie Treaty from 1851, which the <title>Statutes</title>
                        omits), and in most cases, it prints the treaty as <emph>amended</emph> instead of the
                        original treaty with amendments printed at the end, as the <title>Statutes</title> does"
                        (1994, pp. 523-524; emphasis original).<ref n="14" target="n14"/> This may
                        have very well been Kappler's strategy, especially after the critical
                        assessment in 1900 by Commissioner of Indian Affairs Jones regarding
                        previous endeavors &#8212; i.e., "An inaccurate Revision of Indian
                        Treaties then in force was made in 1873. . ." &#8212; that was repeated
                        in 1901 during his third plea for a new suite of critical documents (Annual
                        reports of the Department of the Interior for the fiscal year ended June 30,
                        1900, 1900, p. 50, and Annual reports of the Department of the Interior for
                        the fiscal year ended June 30, 1901, 1901, p. 47). With particular regard to
                        the 1851 <title>Fort Laramie</title> instrument, Kappler presented its full
                        text in both of the 1903 and 1904 <title>Treaties</title> volumes (1903b,
                        pp. 440-442, and 1904b, pp. <ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/sio0594.htm">
                            594-596</ref>).<ref
                            n="15" target="n15"/></p>

                    <p>As a relatively new attorney, and with the admonishments of some
                        Congressional members in mind, it would have been beneficial to Kappler in
                        his quest for completeness to include this treaty in his collation,
                        especially after it had been validated by the Court of Claims opinion for
                            <title>Moore v. United States</title> (1897). In providing a judgment
                        for a depredations case originally involving "the loss of horses, mules, and
                        cattle aggregating in value. . . the sum of $44,335" and for which the
                        Department of the Interior had allowed $17,734 (p. 594),
                            <title>Moore</title> confirmed this instrument as a legitimate and
                        binding transaction between the tribes and the federal government.<ref
                            n="16" target="n16"/> There is, however, no physical proof that this was
                        one of Kappler's stimuli for its addition to <title>Indian Affairs</title>.
                        The problems that arose between the time of the production of the 1903 and
                        1904 texts, and of an explanation in his 1929 volume, only highlight the
                        difficulties that have surrounded the history of these dealings.</p>

                    <p>The 1873 <title>Compilation</title> observed that "The following treaty,
                        though never ratified or printed, is sometimes referred to in appropriations
                        and in other treaties; for instance, treaty with the Sioux, Yancton tribe,
                        proclaimed February 26, 1859. See foot of page 856" (p. 1047).<ref n="17"
                            target="n17"/> The treaty was actually ratified on 24 May 1852, after
                        the original fifty year annuity duration declared in Article 7 was adjusted
                        to a "term of ten years, with the right to continue the same, at the
                        discretion of the President of the United States, for a period not exceeding
                        five years thereafter" (Journal of the Senate of the United States of
                        America, 1852, p. 703). All signatory tribes assented to this alteration,
                        lastly by the Crow in September 1854 (Kappler, 1929, pp. <ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol4/html_files/v4p1065b.html">
                            1079-1080</ref>).
                        In a 1904 footnote, Kappler had mistakenly declared that "[a]ssent of all
                        tribes except the Crows was procured. . . and in subsequent agreements this
                        treaty has been recognized as in force" (Kappler, 1904b, p. <ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/sio0594.htm">
                            594</ref>).<ref
                            n="18" target="n18"/> He corrected this error twenty-five years later in
                        his fourth volume (1929, p. <ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol4/html_files/v4p1065b.html">
                            1065</ref>):
                        "Assent of all tribes was procured, the last acceptance being by the Crows
                        September 18, 1854," i.e., acquired three years after the initial signing
                        date. His reanalysis included the correspondence of Alfred J. Vaughan, the
                        Indian agent who had conveyed to the Crow the annuity duration alteration in
                        Article 7 (1929, pp. 1079-1080). This specific agent had also witnessed the
                        consent given by the Arikara, as revealed in Kappler's 1929 remarks (p.
                            1081).<ref n="19" target="n19"/> Comments on these fresh Vaughan
                        materials were supplied to Kappler by William R. Layne, the "Chief Law
                        Officer" for the Indian Bureau, in an undated letter addressing the overall
                        treaty ratification issue. In his remarks, Layne specifically cited the
                        erroneous assent footnote from volume 2 by "Mr. Kappler, the author of Laws
                        and Treaties" (Kappler, 1929, p. 1067).<ref n="20" target="n20"/></p>

                    <p>There was also an earlier assent explanation. In a memorandum within a report
                        of the Senate Committee on Indian Affairs concerning a special jurisdiction
                        act to empowered the Court of Claims to "hear, examine, adjudicate, and
                        enter judgment in any claims which the Crow Indians may have against the
                        United States" (Claims which the Crow Indians may have against the United
                        States, 1926, p. 1), reference was made to <title>Fort Laramie</title> and
                        specifically to the annuity adjustment. In that remark, it was declared that
                        "[t]his amendment was submitted to the several tribes, parties to the
                        treaty, for ratification, the last ratification being made by the Crows on
                        September 18, 1854" (p. 2). The communication was signed by Charles Kappler
                        and Charles Merillat, as "Attorneys for the Crow Tribe of Indians" and dated
                        26 February 1926.<ref n="21" target="n21"/> The special jurisdiction act was
                        passed on 3 July 1925 (44 <title>Stat.</title> 807), and the resulting
                            <title>Crow Nation or Tribe of Indians of Montana v. United
                            States</title> case was dismissed in 1935.<ref n="22" target="n22"/></p>

                    <p>Thus, it seems likely that Kappler was aware of the Crow assent several years
                        before he actually published his 1929 correction in volume four of
                            <title>Indian Affairs</title>. The firm of Kappler &amp; Merillat
                        had been approached in June 1909 by the Crow to represent them before
                        Congress (Hoxie, 1995, p. 255), but their contract had been cast off in
                        April of 1910 by Commissioner of Indian Affairs Robert Grosvenor Valentine
                        (see Putney, 1979). The firm carried on, without an agreement in place,
                        until mid-1916 (Hoxie, 1995, p. 259, n. 64). In 1923, the tribe
                        re-approached the attorneys, and Commissioner of Indian Affairs Charles
                        Henry Burke (see Kelly, 1979) approved this representation (Hoxie, 1995, p.
                        313) a month after the 1926 passage of the special jurisdiction act.</p>

                    <p>An estimate might thus be calculated for the earliest possible date that
                        Kappler was aware of the Crow concurrence. William R. Layne, the "Chief Law
                        Officer" for the Indian Bureau whose undated letter Kappler had used in 1929
                        to correct his earlier error concerning this event, was listed as "Chief" of
                        the Land Division in the Department of the Interior's travel expense records
                        for a 20 June 1918 trip to Wisconsin (Travel expenses, officers and
                        employees, Department of the Interior, 1929, p. 3). Layne first appeared in
                        the Congressional Directory in 1912 as a "division chief" (Bell, 1912, p.
                        474), suggesting that his position as "Chief Law Officer" was subsequent to
                        this time. If so, then Kappler may have only uncovered his confirmation for
                        the Crow assent in the 1920s.</p>

                    <p>Nevertheless, it remains disappointing to see that this <title>Fort
                            Laramie</title> consent question perseveres, and especially so after the
                        National Archives produced the microfilm collection of <title>Documents
                            Relating to the Negotiation of Ratified and Unratified Treaties with
                            Various Tribes of Indians, 1801-69</title> (1960). Two updates to Felix
                        Cohen's <title>Handbook of Federal Indian Law</title> (1942) stated that
                        assent for the annuity amendment "was never obtained" (Strickland, 1982, p.
                        97), and that "one of the signing tribes never agreed to the amendments"
                        (Newton, 2005, p. 62, n. 392). Both referred to Kappler's 1904 treaty text
                        for support. Strickland's use of an Annual Report of the Commissioner of
                        Indian Affairs to bolster his assertion, though, is damaged because his
                        bibliographic reference is incorrect. Newton's footnote in turn further
                        modified Strickland's use of the Annual Report data, but at least both
                        publications included the <title>Roy</title> (1910) Court of Claim case that
                        certified that the instrument was binding, needless assent errors
                        notwithstanding. Neither of these two later handbooks employed, as Cohen
                        had, the opinion for <title>Crow Nation or Tribe of Indians of Montana v.
                            United States</title> (1935), a case in which Kappler participated. That
                        Court of Claims decision referred directly to his 1929 remarks on the
                        treaty: "The Treaty of Fort Laramie, dated September 17, 1851 (11
                            <title>Stat.</title> 749; 4 Kappler 1065), is as follows:. . ." (p.
                        244), and it cited the agreement process that followed the Congressional
                        annuity article amendment: "The treaty as modified was returned to the
                        tribes concerned and the assent of all was in due course secured, that of
                        the Crow Tribe or Nation September 18, 1854" (p. 248).<ref n="23"
                            target="n23"/> Even today, however, there remains confusion over whether
                        the Crow actually did provide assent (see, for example, Hoig, 2006, p.
                        96).</p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>Development of a new text for <title>Fort Laramie</title></head>
                    <p>This concatenation of events virtually guaranteed that a true and complete
                        version of <title>Fort Laramie</title> never emerged, but the clarity now available
                        regarding this single instrument's history allows for its full presentation
                        today. Observed differences among the releases actually helped create this
                        final product, in part because these materials tendered nearly identical
                        texts that collectively confirmed the expected contents of this
                        transaction.</p>

                    <div3>
                        <head>Text preparation and expectations</head>
                        <p>Test files were composed from each of the seven federal sources. The new
                            files were then re-titled for easy use in this discussion by setting the
                            year of their publication as a suffix; the filenames thus ranged from
                                <title>Laramie51</title> to <title>Laramie29</title>. <ref
                                n="Table1-LED.pdf" type="newwindow">Table I</ref> presents these joint text data. In
                            the case of <title>Laramie51</title>, the contents were derived from
                            digital images of the original treaty kept at the National Archives,
                            while the others were reproduced from microfilm images of the document
                                (<title>Laramie52</title>) or from federal print documents
                                (<title>Laramie72</title> through <title>Laramie29</title>). The
                            suite was converted into word lists devoid of punctuation, deposited
                            into columns of a Microsoft Excel worksheet, and adjusted vertically to
                            align the material. With all punctuation deleted, only the actual
                            wording would thus be compared in subsequent tests.
                                <title>Laramie51</title>, as the original instrument, formed the
                            anchor from which all other files were referenced. Each later document
                            was positioned to align along identical words in
                                <title>Laramie51</title>. For situations where a specific text's
                            material had been confounded by either added or deleted wording
                            &#8212; established, for example, by text incursion errors or, most
                            significantly, by the advent of the annuity adjustment &#8212;
                            vertical column space was interposed in all columns required to accept
                            such changes. An additional document column was reserved for the new
                            proposed <title>Laramie09</title> version. The final, full text proposed for
                                <title>Laramie09</title> returned to the <title>Laramie51</title>
                            text to acquire the original punctuation. In total, eight complete test
                            models of <title>Fort Laramie</title> were formed, all of identical
                            length to reflect both the exclusions and the incursions. This joint
                            text set was the basis of the following comparison testing.</p>
                    </div3>

                    <div3>
                        <head>Text expectations</head>

                        <p>There were six expectations regarding the <title>Fort Laramie</title>
                            versions under examination:</p>

                        <list>
                            <item>The original 1851 treaty text (<title>Laramie51</title>) was
                                considered the standard from which all subsequent renditions
                                evolved. There are known errors in this transcript, primarily those
                                of spelling, but these were reproduced in the final
                                    <title>Laramie09</title> version, just as if the 1851 transaction had
                                been placed directly into the <title>Statutes at
                                Large</title>;</item>
                            <item>The sole modification made to this wording &#8212; through the
                                Senate's annuity amendment &#8212; occurred at the time of
                                ratification. Thus, any newer version requires this correction to
                                Article 7 and this administrative timing thus precludes
                                    <title>Laramie51</title> and <title>Laramie52</title> from
                                representing the true text;</item>
                            <item>The text created by the Senate for their confidential
                                consideration (Articles of a treaty, 1852; <title>Laramie52</title>)
                                was assumed to be the best initial reproduction of the 1851
                                material. This Executive Document was dated five months after the
                                original negotiations, and the Journal of the Senate of the United
                                States of America (1852) recorded the events in the legislative life
                                of this instrument. Such actions entailed the document's submission
                                to the Senate by President Fillmore on 13 February 1852; its initial
                                reading and the confidential printing order on the 17th; and then a
                                report from the Committee on Indian Affairs on 19 April declaring
                                that no amendments were made to it (pp. 700-701). Finally, on 24 May
                                1852, the "advise and consent to the ratification of the articles of
                                a treaty made and concluded at Fort Laramie" were given, along with
                                the agreed annuity revision (pp. 702-703). The exact new payment
                                specification was: "Article 7, strike out the words "fifty years,"
                                and insert in lieu thereof the following: the term of ten years,
                                with the right to continue same, at the discretion of the President
                                of the United States, for a period not exceeding five years
                                thereafter" (p. 703). These activities support the contention that,
                                commencing on 24 May 1852, the new official federal version of
                                    <title>Fort Laramie</title> would have been a concatenation of
                                    <title>Laramie51</title> (as most probably observed by the
                                Senate through <title>Laramie52</title>) and this chamber's thirty
                                word allowance alteration to Article 7;</item>
                            <item>Any subsequent versions of the treaty, including the ones from
                                1873, 1884, or any of those submitted by Kappler, should exhibit
                                identical text &#8212; solely reflecting the results of that
                                limited Senate intervention &#8212; since each federal
                                publication request had been made for a <emph>current</emph>
                                official compilation of treaties affecting the tribes;
                                    <emph>current</emph> would have meant the entire document
                                ratified by the Senate on 24 May 1852. Thus, the materials found in
                                    <title>Laramie73</title>, <title>Laramie84</title>,
                                    <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and
                                    <title>Laramie29</title> should, for all intents and purposes,
                                be indistinguishable from each other;</item>
                            <item>Within all these documents, it became apparent that tribal name
                                spellings were particularly susceptible to variation. Kappler's use
                                of the "Names of Indian tribes and bands" list, proposed by the
                                Office of Indian Affairs in conjunction with the Bureau of Ethnology
                                (Kappler, 1904a, p. 1021), was reserved exclusively to his document
                                titles and was not applied to the transaction contents. Precedents
                                for such name allegiance appear in the <title>Statutes at
                                    Large</title>. Here, the Pottawatomie were the prototypic
                                example of a tribe to which a multiplicity of names had been
                                applied, indeed so abundantly that a footnote to the title of the
                                1846 <title>Treaty with the Pottowautomie Nation</title> (9
                                    <title>Stat.</title> 853) declared: "The name of this tribe is,
                                in different treaties, spelled very differently."<ref n="24"
                                    target="n24"/> Their name in this specific
                                    <title>Statutes</title> entry was a substantial deviation from
                                the others. Kappler's version of their name, taken from the "Names"
                                list, was <title><ref
                                    n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/kindex3.htm#P">
                                    Potawatomi</ref></title>, as it appeared for them in the
                                Index to the <title>Treaties</title> volume, and as it is revealed
                                in his title, the <title><ref
                                    n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/pot0557.htm">
                                    Treaty with the Potawatomi Nation,
                                    1846</ref></title> (1904b, pp. 1089-1090 and pp. 557-560, respectively). Beyond the title, his text reflected the contents
                                found in the <title>Statutes</title>, regardless of any spelling
                                differences, a choice that had been very clearly determined in
                                February 1903 when he wrote in the Preface to <title>Laws</title>:
                                "At the suggestion of the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, the
                                correct modern spelling of Indian names, as decided by the Indian
                                Office and the Bureau of Ethnology, has been introduced and adopted
                                in the headlines to the treaties, <emph>but in the text it was found
                                    expedient to follow the orthography of the Statutes</emph>"
                                (1903a, p. iii; emphasis added);<ref n="25" target="n25"/>
                                and</item>
                            <item>The Kappler accounts furnished by <title>Laramie03</title>,
                                    <title>Laramie04</title>, and <title>Laramie29</title> should
                                match closely, even to the point of sharing errors. This should be
                                especially so when the first two examples are considered, since the
                                transition between their publications allegedly differed only by the
                                addition in 1904 of the original testimonium and accompanying
                                signature sections that were absent from the 1903 presentation.
                                Kappler prefaced the second edition of <title>Treaties</title> with
                                the statement that "[t]he new edition has afforded the compiler an
                                opportunity to make such typographical and other corrections as were
                                discovered in the first print, to insert several treaties and
                                documents which were heretofore unobtainable, and to add the
                                signatures subscribed to each treaty which was omitted in the first
                                edition to save space" (1904a, p. v).</item>
                        </list>
                    </div3>

                    <div3>
                        <head>Test processes and results</head>
                        <p>A three-stage comparison process was conducted. First, an assessment was
                            made between <title>Laramie51</title> and <title>Laramie52</title> of
                            the joint text set, i.e., between the data columns containing the two
                            unadjusted annuity texts. This was considered important because any
                            differences found between the wording of the original treaty and that of
                            the latter text, submitted to the Senate to determine the fate of that
                            transaction, would be expected to materialize in any subsequent
                            publication. Second, the three Kappler records &#8212;
                                <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and
                                <title>Laramie29</title> &#8212; were examined for internal
                            consistency, and in order to form an understanding of his suite.
                            Finally, differences were determined between <title>Laramie51</title>
                            and each of <title>Laramie73</title>, <title>Laramie84</title>,
                                <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and
                                <title>Laramie29</title> to collect text discrepancies. These
                            observed variations guided the development of a composite text that was
                            designed to reflect better the original transaction's words, affected
                            only by the Senate's later modification to them. The full text version
                            of that outcome is found in the Appendix as <title>Laramie09</title>,
                            along with each of the earlier documents. The term <term>composite
                                text</term> is used hereafter to identify this new version of
                                <title>Fort Laramie</title>.</p>

                        <p>The results of these comparisons express unequivocally that six accurate
                            reflections of the original <title>Laramie51</title> text were never
                            accomplished. The later contracts were found to be riddled with
                            inconsistencies when considered against the primary instrument,<ref
                                n="26" target="n26"/> yet in this study &#8212; just as in those
                            of Channing and Carter &#8212; not every difference was perceived as
                            a catastrophic error. However, the exclusion of <title>Laramie51</title>
                            material from succeeding descriptions and a text incursion only present
                            in <title>Laramie29</title> certainly were considered major deviations
                            from the original treaty. This was especially so because the text
                            exclusion undermined the parameters of the 1851 contract, while the
                                <title>Laramie29</title> incursion befouled a reservation
                            specification. Nevertheless, slight spelling differences overall were
                            considered more in line with everyday transcription inaccuracies. The
                            later use of the term <term>the</term> instead of <term>these</term>, of
                                <term>principal</term> instead of <term>principals</term>, or of
                            even <term>$50,000</term> instead of <term>fifty thousand dollars</term>
                            was tolerable. Truncating <term>Article</term> to <term>Art</term> (or
                            marking such paragraphs with <term>VIII</term> or <term>8</term> instead
                            of <term>8th</term>) was considered as noise created during
                            reproduction. Ultimately, though, the new composite text returned to the
                            orthography of the original 1851 document, because the goal was to
                            understand the actual legal expression of the transaction. <ref
                                n="Table1-LED.pdf" type="newwindow">Table I</ref>
                            provides colored line numbers &#8212; 183 in all &#8212; to
                            identify the full range of dissimilarities found across the array of
                                <title>Laramie51</title> through <title>Laramie29</title>.</p>
                    </div3>

                    <div3>
                        <head>Observed differences</head>

                        <p>In general, four error types were observed from these analyses:
                            exclusion; incursion; replacement; and amendment:</p>

                        <list>
                            <item>The sole exclusion involved material from <title>Laramie51</title>
                                that failed to appear in the 1873, 1903, 1904, and 1929 versions.
                                This absence may be seen across lines 471-477 of the joint text set;
                                the original material consisted of a seven-word phrase in the fifth
                                Article's boundary description for the Gros Ventre, Mandan, and
                                Arikara.</item>
                            <item>Incursions occurred when text was inserted during the preparation
                                of other accounts, relative to the original 1851 wording. Lines
                                353-368 reveal a sixteen-word redundant section of
                                    <title>Laramie29</title>. An insignificant example of this type
                                of error would be the addition of the term <term>the</term> at line
                                333 of <title>Laramie73</title>, <title>Laramie03</title>,
                                    <title>Laramie04</title>, and <title>Laramie29</title>.</item>
                            <item>Cases of simple replacement are prevalent; see the spelling
                                examples below.</item>
                            <item>Finally, the amendment process impels adaptations to the text of
                                    <title>Laramie51</title> in order to reflect the Senate annuity
                                adjustment to Article 7. Lines 1026-1055 divulge how the joint text
                                set &#8212; and especially <title>Laramie09</title> &#8212;
                                were constructed to handle that necessary annuity alteration by
                                substituting the adjustment's thirty words for the first two
                                original treaty ones.</item>
                        </list>

                        <p>Absent the terms <term>Superintent</term>, <term>behavior</term>,
                                <term>maintainance</term>, and (Santa) <term>F&#234;</term>
                            discussed below, examples of alternative spellings occurred, exemplified
                            perhaps by <term>alonge</term> in <title>Laramie73</title> (see line 492
                            in the joint text set). Further, the terms <term>head chiefs</term>,
                                <term>head men</term>, <term>fifty one</term>, <term>north
                                westerly</term>, <term>south-easterly</term> and <term>south
                                easterly</term>, <term>south-westerly</term>, and <term>Yellow
                                Stone</term> were used in <title>Laramie51</title>, while post-1851
                            documents employed <term>headmen</term>, <term>fifty-one</term>,
                                <term>northwesterly</term>, <term>southeasterly</term>,
                                <term>southwesterly</term>, and <term>Yellowstone</term>.
                            Specifically, <term>head waters</term>, <term>Muscle-Shell</term>,
                                <term>Twenty five Yard</term> and <term>Twenty-five Yard</term> were
                            applied within <title>Laramie51</title>, whereas the variants
                                <term>headwaters</term> or <term>head-waters</term>, <term>Muscle
                                Shell</term> and <term>Muscle-shell</term>, and
                                <term>Twenty-five-yard</term> surfaced in some subsequent texts.</p>
                    </div3>

                    <div3>
                        <head>Four special terms</head>
                        <p>Four tokens stand out as unique elements of the original treaty text,
                            primarily because of their orthography. These have little influence or
                            significance within the transaction, but their usage provides a unique
                            window upon the times and, perhaps even more so, upon Adam B. Chambers,
                            who served as Secretary during the negotiations and who had made a
                            career as a journalist. A search was made for each of these four items
                            within the pages of the <title>United States Congressional Serial
                                Set</title> around the time of <title>Fort Laramie</title> to
                            certify their contemporary use. In addition, the legal aspects of this
                            treaty were subsequently tested before the courts, so appropriate
                            opinions were examined for the application of these expressions as
                            well.</p>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <term>Superintent</term>
                            </head>
                            <list>
                                <item>This word emerges in the <title>Serial Set</title> in
                                    testimony given during a federal investigation into the sale of
                                    Fort Snelling in 1857 (Fort Snelling investigation, 1858, p. 2;
                                    Jones, 1966, pp. 230-231). On 23 February 1858, William J.
                                    Cullen, Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Northern
                                    Superintendency (see Hill, 1974, pp. 118-120), responded to the
                                    question "What is your office?" by stating
                                        "<term>Superintent</term> of Indian Affairs" (Fort Snelling
                                    investigation, 1858, p. 264; emphasis added).<ref n="27"
                                        target="n27"/> As announced in the 1851 preamble with this
                                    aberrant spelling, D. D. (David D.) Mitchell was the
                                    Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Central
                                    Superintendency, following his appointment on 13 March 1851,
                                    i.e., just six months before <title>Fort Laramie</title> was
                                    consummated. He had served in the same role for the St. Louis
                                    Superintendency, which was then replaced in 1851 by the Central
                                    office. William Clark, of Lewis and Clark fame, was the first
                                    Superintendent in St. Louis, beginning in 1822 (Hill, 1974, pp.
                                    28-31 and 155-159). Thomas Fitzpatrick was the initial Agent for
                                    the Upper Platte Agency when it was established in 1846 and he
                                    was serving in that capacity at the time of <title>Fort
                                        Laramie</title>. The Agency was assigned to the St.
                                    Louis-Central Superintendency, thus sealing Fitzpatrick's
                                    connection with Mitchell that was announced in the treaty's
                                    preamble. The President thus employed the two most appropriate
                                    and experienced federal representatives as commissioners: both
                                    men had had extensive interactions with the tribes present at
                                    the event (pp. 188-189).</item>
                                <item>The word was exercised more recently before the Indian Claims
                                    Commission, a tribunal created specifically to address
                                    unresolved Indian legal questions. The opinion for <title>The
                                        Confederated Tribes of the Warm Springs Reservation of
                                        Oregon v. United States</title> remarked: "However, if the
                                    three "principal bands, to wit: the Wascopurn, Tiah or Upper De
                                    Chutes, and the Lower De Chutes bands" desired to select a
                                    committee, and if such committee and the
                                        <title>Superintent</title> of Indian Affairs or his agent
                                    were successful in finding a more suitable location for a
                                    reservation, then "the same shall be declared a reservation for
                                    said Indians, instead of the tract named in this treaty"" (1963,
                                    p. 667; emphasis added).<ref n="28" target="n28"/>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </div4>

                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <term>Behaviour</term>
                            </head>
                            <list>
                                <item>This specific spelling is presented in <title>The Oxford
                                        English Dictionary</title> (1989, vol. 2, pp. 73-74).
                                    Traditionally, the additional <term>u</term> has been a part of English, and
                                    not American, orthography to create such terms as
                                        <term>colour</term>, <term>flavour</term>,
                                        <term>honour</term>, <term>labour</term>,
                                        <term>neighbour</term>, <term>harbour</term>, and
                                        <term>tumour</term> (Ritter, 2003, p. 238).
                                        <term>Behaviour</term> is one such manifestation.</item>
                                <item>Interestingly, it surfaces as well in the <title>Statutes at
                                        Large</title> in <title>An act to establish a court for the
                                        investigation of claims against the United States</title>
                                    (1855), i.e., for the creation of the United States Court of
                                    Claims before which a number of American Indian treaties
                                    &#8212; including <title>Fort Laramie</title> &#8212;
                                    were cited. The act indicated "[t]hat a court shall be
                                    established to be called the Court of Claims, to consist of
                                    three judges, to be appointed by the President, by and with the
                                    consent of the Senate, and to hold their offices during good
                                    <term>behaviour</term>. . .." (p. 612; emphasis added).<ref n="29"
                                        target="n29"/> Further, before the later Indian Claims
                                    Commission, the term was delivered in <title>Oneida Nation of
                                        New York v. United States</title>: "On August 15, 1778, the
                                    Commissioners for Indian Affairs in the Northern Department met
                                    with deputies from the Onondaga Indians who tried to excuse
                                    their recent hostile <term>behaviour</term>" (1971, p. 604;
                                    emphasis added).</item>
                            </list>
                        </div4>

                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <term>Maintainance</term>
                            </head>
                            <list>
                                <item>This token is found in <title>The Oxford English
                                        Dictionary</title>, as an entry under
                                        <term>maintenance</term> (1989, vol. 9, pp. 225-226).</item>
                                <item>It is also present in <title>An act making appropriations for
                                        the support of the Army for the fiscal year ending June
                                        thirtieth, 1877, and for other purposes</title> in the
                                        <title>Statutes at Large</title> in which funds were
                                    earmarked: "For maintaining and improving national military
                                    cemeteries, one hundred and twenty-five thousand dollars:
                                    Provided, The Secretary of War shall provide for the care and
                                        <term>maintainance</term> of the National Cemeteries and..."
                                    (1876, p. 99; emphasis added).</item>
                                <item>The Indian Claims Commission opinion for <title>Confederated
                                        Tribes of Colville Reservation v. United States</title> made
                                    use of this expression as well: "Defendant spent large amounts
                                    of money in fish protection, and in <term>maintainance</term>
                                    thereafter, not to protect claimants' fishing rights, but for
                                    the preservation of the species" (1978, p. 539; emphasis
                                    added).</item>
                            </list>
                        </div4>

                        <div4>
                            <head><term>F&#234;</term></head>
                            <list>
                                <item>This was a clear misuse of the circumflex. This diacritical
                                    mark is not used in Spanish (Errapel Mejias-Vicandi, personal
                                    communication, 4 June 2009), but its appearance provides an
                                    interesting &#8212; indeed, an intriguing &#8212;
                                    manifestation of the errors made by those who wrote these
                                    instruments. Most of today's applications, including for the
                                    name of the capital of New Mexico, are satisfied with the term
                                        <term>Fe</term>. In Spanish, it appears as
                                        <term>F&#233;</term>, with the acute.</item>
                            </list>
                        </div4>
                    </div3>

                    <div3>

                        <head>Other discrepancies</head>

                        <p>As noted above, Clarence E. Carter identified abundant punctuation errors
                            in the <title>Treaty with the Wyandots, etc., 1789</title> and the
                                <title>Treaty with the Wyandots, etc., 1795</title> when he made
                            direct comparisons between the original treaties and their Kappler
                            equivalents. Overall, such faults persist here, when each of the
                            examined federal versions of <title>Fort Laramie</title> was compared
                            with the original 1851 treaty. One such difficulty may be seen in the
                            various renderings of, and in the punctuation surrounding, the special
                            term <term>viz</term>. &#8212; "in reading aloud usually rendered by 'namely'"
                                (<title>The Oxford English Dictionary</title>, 1989, vol. 19, p.
                            718) &#8212; that is present once in the preamble and then again in
                            each document's first paragraph of Article 5. The observed pairs consist
                            of &#8212; <term>viz:</term> and <term>viz:</term> &#8212; in
                                <title>Laramie51</title>; <term>viz:</term> and <term>viz :</term>
                            in <title>Laramie52</title>; <term>viz</term>, and <term>viz:</term> in
                                <title>Laramie73</title>, <title>Laramie03</title>,
                                <title>Laramie04</title>, and <title>Laramie29</title>; and
                                <term>viz:</term> and <term>viz:</term> in <title>Laramie84</title>.
                            Note that none of these included the terminal period &#8212; as in
                                <term>viz.</term> &#8212; found elsewhere.<ref n="30"
                                target="n30"/> Nevertheless, the unpunctuated token <term>viz</term>
                            is found in the texts of seven Indian treaties in volume 11 of the
                                <title>Statutes</title>, along with the <title>Fort Laramie</title>
                            treaty stub at 11 <title>Stat.</title> 749.<ref n="31" target="n31"/>
                            Thus, the shorter term <term>viz</term> must have been an acceptable representation
                            at the time Adam B. Chambers constructed this document for the treaty
                            meeting.</p>

                        <p>The variability of tribal names alone contributed to a considerable
                            number of differences among the treaty text files. Importantly, the same
                            tribe name was commonly spelled in more than one way within a single
                            document &#8212; the initial <title>Laramie51</title> began such
                            deviation with <term>Gros-Ventres</term> and <term>Gros Ventre</term>
                            &#8212; but such unpredictability has been widespread over the
                            years. In his important study on the tribes, Hodge (1907a) provided
                            2,500 various spellings of tribe names and definitive sources to address
                            questions arising from such dissimilarities. Among his options may be
                            found optional spellings created by the Bureau of Indian Affairs for use
                            in its own Annual Reports: e.g., Aripohoes or Arrapahas (p. 73);
                            Arickare or Arickarees (p. 86); and Assinepoins or Assinib'wans (pp.
                            104-105). Such general inconsistencies persisted until 1900, at which
                            time they were mitigated to some degree by the advent of the "Names of
                            Indian tribes and bands" list (Annual reports of the Department of the
                            Interior for the fiscal year ended June 30, 1900, p. 51). <ref
                                n="Table2-LED.pdf" type="newwindow">Table II</ref> contains the nineteen tribal names
                            used in the preambles and in Article 5 of each of the seven instrument
                            versions. The final column contains for comparison the preferred tribe
                            name as define by that "Names of Indian tribes and bands" assembly. This
                            Bureau collection was considered an important step towards a
                            standardization of entity spellings, and was an exhibition of the new
                            federal desire for order that emerged in the last decade of the
                            nineteenth century.<ref n="32" target="n32"/> As Table II illustrates,
                            the Sioux were given an additional name, which all versions except for
                                <title>Laramie52</title> have as <term>Dacotahs</term>.<ref n="33"
                                target="n33"/> The preambles hold nine of the nineteen names, in its
                            effort to identify the eight active participants at the negotiations.
                            Article 5, on the other hand, sequentially specified land parameters for
                            all relevant groups, including a ninth tribe &#8212; the
                                <term>Blackfeet</term> &#8212; who, although absent, had their
                            reservation set by these negotiations.</p>

                        <p>Overall, all documents maintained the spellings for <term>Sioux</term>,
                                <term>Cheyennes</term>, and <term>Arrapahoes</term>. In the preamble
                            section, the terms <term>Crows</term> and <term>Mandans</term> were also
                            similar across instruments, while in Article 5, <term>Crow</term> was
                            used by all. Various spellings prevailed for <term>Assiniboine</term>,
                                <term>Gros Ventre</term>, <term>Mandan</term>, <term>Arikara</term>,
                            and <term>Blackfeet</term>, ranging from the addition of a pluralizing
                                <term>s</term> (<term>Mandans</term>), to an intervening hyphen
                                (<term>Gros-Ventre</term>), to bifurcating names (<term>Black
                                Foot</term>), to substantial spelling deviations
                                (<term>Arreckera</term>, <term>Arickaree</term>, and
                                <term>Arrickaras</term>). Other changes in spelling, capitalization,
                            and abbreviation occurred as well, just as Prucha had noticed before
                            (1994, p. 445).</p>

                        <p>As stated earlier, the sole exclusion of original treaty text from
                                <title>Laramie73</title> and from the three Kappler documents
                            &#8212; while still appearing in <title>Laramie52</title> and
                                <title>Laramie84</title> &#8212; contributed to the boundaries
                            paragraph for the Gros Ventre, Mandan, and Arikara (joint text set,
                            lines 471-477). This omission was considered a serious error,<ref n="34"
                                target="n34"/> whereas the assorted incursions presented both major
                            and minor divergences. One distinct major incursion may be found in the
                            Sioux subparagraph of <title>Laramie29</title>'s Article 5, where
                            unnecessary material &#8212; . . .<term>thence up the north fork of
                                the Platte River to the forks of the Platte River</term>. . .
                            &#8212; became visible in the text (lines 353-368). This error is
                            absent in every other <title>Fort Laramie</title> example. Minor
                            incursions may be illustrated by the insertion of the term
                                <term>at</term> in the phrase <term>The territory of the Sioux or
                                Dahcotah nation Commencing <hi rend="bold">at</hi> the mouth of
                                White river</term> (lines 320-336; emphasis added) in
                                <title>Laramie51</title>, <title>Laramie52</title>,
                                <title>Laramie84</title>, and <title>Laramie29</title>, yet this is
                            paralleled by its absence and by the minor incursion of the term
                                <term>the</term> in <term>The territory of the Sioux or Dahcotah
                                nation commencing the mouth of <hi rend="bold">the</hi> White
                                River</term> (emphasis added) found in <title>Laramie73</title>,
                                <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and
                                <title>Laramie29</title>. In these instances, the
                                <title>Laramie29</title> text involves both minor incursions. There
                            is an unexpected benefit, however, attached to these findings, because
                            repeated couplings of textual difficulties in <title>Laramie73</title>
                            and the three Kappler copies collectively reinforce the consideration
                            that Kappler modeled his 1903, and subsequent materials, from the 1873
                            transcript.</p>

                        <p>Word replacement similarly induced both classes of errors. In the minor
                            category, dissimilarities reflect simple substitutions, such as in
                            Article 6 of <title>Laramie51</title> that begins with the phrase
                                <term>The parties of the Second part <hi rend="bold">to</hi> this
                                treaty, having selected principal or Head Chiefs for <hi rend="bold"
                                    >their</hi> respective nations</term>. . ..
                                <title>Laramie52</title>, on the other hand, has <term>The parties
                                of the second part <hi rend="bold">of</hi> this treaty, having
                                selected principal or head chiefs for <hi rend="bold">these</hi>
                                respective nations</term>. . . (lines 923-942; emphasis added). Such
                            faults may also appear in combination. For Article 7,
                                <title>Laramie51</title> declares <term>In consideration of <hi
                                    rend="bold">these</hi> treaty stipulations, and for the damages
                                which have, or may occur by reason thereof, to the Indian Nations
                                &#8212; parties hereto, and for their maintainance, and the
                                improvement of their moral and social <hi rend="bold"
                                >condition</hi>,</term>. . ., whereas <title>Laramie73</title>
                            remarks <term>In consideration of <hi rend="bold">the</hi> treaty
                                stipulations, and for the damages which have or may occur by reason
                                thereof to the Indian nations, parties hereto, and for their
                                maintenance and the improvement of their moral and social <hi
                                    rend="bold">customs,</hi></term>..." (lines 968-1004; emphasis
                            added). The <term>condition</term>/<term>customs</term> distinction is
                            considered here as a major replacement error, while the
                                <term>these</term>/<term>the</term> or the
                                <term>maintainance</term>/<term>maintenance</term> inaccuracies are
                            not.</p>

                        <p>One of the clearest replacement illustrations occurs in the final segment
                            of Article 5. In the original transaction in 1851, a proviso to the
                            treaty reads: . . .<term>they do not surrender the privilege of hunting,
                                fishing or passing over any of the tracts of Country <hi rend="bold"
                                    >hereinbefore</hi> described</term> (lines 901-920; emphasis
                            added). The term <term>hereinbefore</term> is replicated only in the
                            Senate's copy and in <title>Laramie84</title>. <title>Laramie73</title>,
                                <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and
                                <title>Laramie29</title> each have <term>heretofore</term>, thereby providing
                            further evidence that Kappler employed <title>Laramie73</title> as the
                            prototype for his compilations.</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>The Senate-imposed annuity adjustment</head>
                    <p>Following the modification instituted by the Senate and evident for the first
                        time in the <title>Laramie73</title> document, the final text of Article 7
                        reduced the duration of the promised 1851 annuity from "the sum of Fifty
                        thousand dollars per annum <term>for fifty years</term> in provisions,
                        merchandize, domestic animals and agricultural implement, in such
                        proportions as may be deemed best adapted to their condition, by the
                        President of the United States &#8212; to be distributed in proportion
                        to the population of the aforesaid Indian nations" to "the sum of fifty
                        thousand dollars per annum <term>for the term of ten years, with the right
                            to continue the same, at the discretion of the President of the United
                            States, for a period not exceeding five years thereafter</term>, in
                        provisions, merchandise, domestic animals, and agricultural implements, in
                        such proportions as may be deemed best adapted to their condition by the
                        President of the United States, to be distributed in proportion to the
                        population of the aforesaid Indian nations" (emphasis added).
                            <title>Laramie52</title>, as the Senate's working copy of the original,
                        and <title>Laramie84</title> did not present this correction, but reproduced the original
                        1851 passage. While the annuity modification had no place in the original
                        transaction or in the 1852 material, the absence from the 1884 <title>Laws
                            of the United States Relating to Indian Affairs</title> of the
                        specifications for this monumental change must have been a further
                        irritation to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs. Kappler's three versions
                        in 1903, 1904, and 1929 supplied the appropriate new parameters, although
                        the last document engaged the terms <term>$50,000</term> and <term>10
                            years</term> for the allowance amount and its duration.</p>

                    <p>In a contrast between the outcomes of text replacement and text amendment
                        within this particular document, it may be concluded that the former yielded
                        inappropriate changes to the contents, whereas the latter procedure updated
                        the original treaty in a legally acceptable manner. All four adaptive
                        processes &#8212; exclusion, intrusion, replacement, and amendment
                        &#8212; found in these various perspectives upon <title>Fort
                            Laramie</title> supply critical provenance data, and help explain in
                        part how Kappler might have used the previously published renditions to
                        create his <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and
                            <title>Laramie29</title>. Thus, several similarities strongly recommend
                        a bond between the text of <title>Laramie73</title> and that of
                            <title>Laramie03</title>, yet simultaneously separate these attempts
                        from both the National Archives' original document and the
                            <title>Laramie84</title> instrument. The presence of the "never ratified
                        or printed" note before each of the 1873 and 1903 preambles is a substantial
                        signal that Kappler just merely reproduced the 1873 source for his 1903
                        edition of <title>Treaties</title>. The change from <term>Yancton</term> to
                            <term>Yankton</term> in that message, though, indicates some undefined
                        level of intervention, but this fine-tuning corresponds to that seen in
                        Kappler's new treaty titles that promptly conveyed his adherence to the
                        "Names of Indian tribes and bands" inventory recommendations.<ref n="35"
                            target="n35"/></p>

                    <p>Further 1873/1903 resemblances are at hand. The specific spelling of the
                        terms <term>Arrickaras</term> in Kappler's preamble and in Article 5, and of
                            <term>Assinaboin</term> in the latter portion, are present only in the
                        1873 material. The plural <term>Assinaboines</term> is an element of both preambles. The
                        hyphenated <term>Gros-Ventre</term> tribe name in these suggests
                        that it was carried forward from 1873 to 1903 as a textual misunderstanding.
                        Here, inspection of the 1873 reproduction shows that there was a split
                        between two lines of text, with the <term>Ventre</term> part located on the
                        following line, which perhaps resulted in an ensuing mistakenly applied
                        hyphen thought necessary to link the two portions. In addition, there is an
                        absent comma between the terms <term>Gros-Ventre</term> and <term>Mandans</term> in the preamble that
                        is only evident in the 1873 rendition. The term <term>to</term> in the sixth
                        Article phrase <term>The parties <hi rend="bold">to</hi> the second part of
                            this treaty</term>. . . is used in both the 1873 and in the Kappler
                        texts, while the National Archive document and the 1884 <title>Laws</title>
                        text examples employ the term <term>of</term> in their remark <term>The
                            parties <hi rend="bold">of</hi> the second part of this treaty</term>. .
                        . (joint text set lines 923-932).</p>

                    <p>Later modifications appear in Kappler's 1929 work that further distances that
                        attempt from the original. This republication &#8212; its title reduced
                        now to just the <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie, 1851</title> &#8212;
                        contained several preamble alterations. In this rendition, the <term>Gros Ventre</term>
                        hyphenation has now disappeared, and the appropriate comma between this
                        tribe name and that of the <term>Mandan</term> has materialized. Article 5 exhibits a new
                        spelling for <term>Assinaboine</term> with a final <term>e</term> (joint
                        text set line 516), which neither the 1852, the 1873, the 1903, nor the 1904
                        version possesses. Article 6 clumsily combines the <term>to</term> and the
                            <term>of</term> present in the original, the 1873, and the 1884
                        renditions to declare "The parties <term>to</term>(<term>of</term>) the
                        second part of this treaty. . ." (p. 1066; emphasis added).</p>

                    <p>Kappler was empowered by the Senate to compile the texts of valid American
                        Indian treaties with the federal government. The second volume of
                            <title>Indian Affairs</title> was the result of this endeavor,
                        coordinating the <emph>final</emph> texts of such transactions. One manner
                        in which this terminal condition may be assessed is through the notations
                        supplied by Kappler to about a dozen and a half instruments that identified
                        in those situations deleted or amended articles. For example, in the very
                        short <title><ref
                            n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/pot0450.htm">
                            Treaty with the Potawatomi, 1836</ref></title>, Kappler amended
                        Article 6 &#8212; virtually half of the entire text of this contract and
                        defined to reserve land for one Henry Ossum &#8212; to read "[Stricken
                        out by the Senate]" (Kappler, 1904b, p. 450).<ref
                            n="36" target="n36"/> The entire event appears in the <title>Statutes at
                            Large</title> (7 <title>Stat.</title> 490), but a footnote conveys that "This article
                        (Art. 6) was not ratified." The conclusive or final treaty parameters of
                        this, or of any other treaties, were very much the focus of the 1902 Senate
                        resolution to create a well-indexed compilation. Under that request, and
                        even though available through some previous federal endeavor(s), it seems
                        reasonable to conclude that Kappler would not have used the <title>Fort
                            Laramie</title> document found in the 1884 <title>Laws of the United
                            States Relating to Indian Affairs</title> precisely because that
                        assembly offered only the <emph>original</emph> 1851 text of the
                        transaction. The preceding 1873 <title>Compilation</title>, on the other
                        hand, had already incorporated the Senate's adjusted annuity
                        determination.</p>

                    <p>Absent all the variations in the contents of these documents, whatever their
                        cause, there is a succinct revelation of their collective inability to
                        deliver a final copy of the true contents of the intended treaty. In this
                        scenario and as advocated earlier, <emph>the true contents of the intended
                            treaty</emph> are considered to consist of the wording agreed to by all
                        parties on 17 September 1851 that was later modified only through Senate
                        involvement. In terms of the number of words necessary to make the 1851
                        document accurately reflect the true combination of these two events, two
                        tokens in Article 7 must be replaced by the thirty that convey the annuity
                        redefinition. This maneuver effectively excluded the original 1851 and
                            <title>Laramie52</title>, but it also eliminated the later
                            <title>Laramie84</title> that had reproduced the outdated 1851 text. In
                        comparison, only <title>Laramie73</title> and each of Kappler's three
                        subsequent instruments brought forward that requisite correction. However,
                        each of those four properly updated versions produced in 1873, 1903, 1904,
                        and 1929 concurrently suffered from the absence of the seven-word phrase
                            <term>thence from the mouth of Powder River</term> that was part of the
                        reservation bounds set for the Gros Ventre, Mandan, and Arikara in Article 5
                        of <title>Laramie51</title> (joint text set lines 471-477). In combination,
                        these errors cause every published text between 1851 and 1929 to fail in one
                        way or another to carry the final version of the intended treaty.</p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>Presenting the new text</head>

                    <p>Thus, the comparison of all texts &#8212; <title>Laramie51</title>
                        through <title>Laramie29</title> &#8212; formed an important beginning
                        for the creation of the new, correct composite one that adheres to the
                        original 1851 material. This standardization against
                            <title>Laramie51</title> is not without peril. The treaty begins almost
                        immediately with its own problems, illustrated by <term>Superintent</term>
                        in the preamble. Yet Aust (2007, p. 315) dispensed a general remark
                        pertaining to the design of treaties. He observed that "[b]ecause the
                        treaty-making process is such that risk of material errors is reduced to the
                        minimum, almost all the recorded cases where error has been involved to
                        invalidate a treaty have concerned mistakes in maps." To this he added that
                        such document errors "may be typographical, spelling, punctuation, numbering
                        or cross-referencing, or a lack of concordance between the authentic
                        language texts. It may be a simple drafting mistake, such as the use of
                        inconsistent terminology. But correcting anything which is more than an
                        obvious 'physical' error, or mistake of spelling or numbering, may affect
                        the substance. Punctuation is an aspect of grammar which is perhaps more
                        crucial for some languages, including English, than others which have more
                        certain grammatical rules" (p. 315).<ref n="37" target="n37"/> The six texts
                        published by the federal government between 1852 and 1929 have many of these
                        shortfalls, in one form or another. Indeed, the present discussion only
                        exists because Aust's "lack of concordance" among these "authentic language
                        texts" is abundantly evident. Individually, these documents reflect in part
                        the technical problems that accompanied publishing in the second half of the
                        nineteenth century, let alone their construction in the field, but a portion
                        of those difficulties arose because care was absent in later reproductions.
                        Collectively, this latter ambivalence triggers further questions about other
                        published Indian treaties, as well as virtually all the texts found in the
                        volumes of the <title>Statutes at Large</title>.</p>

                    <p>This presentation strategy, designed to circumvent past shortfalls
                        originating in the copies of <title>Fort Laramie</title>, is not unique.
                        Arends and Van den Berg (2004) created a new text &#8212; in Sranan, a
                        Creole language, with English passage equivalents &#8212; for the 1762
                            <title>Saramaka Peace Treaty</title> between the Dutch and the Saramaka
                        Maroons of Suriname (Price, 1983a and b). In that instance, the official
                        Dutch version was accessible almost immediately after signing, but the
                        indigenous interpretation only became available in this century. The authors
                        acknowledged that they had supplied this new material in order "to make this
                        text available to the community of creolists as one more addition to the
                        ever growing corpus of early Surinamese Creole texts in the hope that it
                        will contribute to a better understanding of the history of creole languages
                        and societies in Suriname and beyond." Parameter declarations within that
                        document &#8212; such as "All the Bush Negroes of the Upper Saramaka and
                        the Upper Suriname (Rivers) will have peace with all Whites of Suriname, and
                        the Whites will forget all the bad things they have done" &#8212; mirror
                        analogous comments found in <title>Fort Laramie</title> that also express
                        expected behaviors by all parties.</p>

                    <p>The overall format of <title>Laramie09</title> simulates what the contract
                        might have looked like if it had joined other instruments in the eleventh
                        volume of the <title>Statutes of Large</title>. The final assent of the Crow
                        to the revised annuity occurred on 18 September 1854 and the <title>Treaty
                            with the Ottoes and Missourias</title> (11 <title>Stat.</title> 605) &#8212; signed
                        on 9 December 1854 &#8212; was therefore used as the closest
                        chronological <title>Statutes</title> example. Kappler's full title for
                            <title>Fort Laramie</title> is maintained, since apparently no other
                        official name was created: the original transaction had no document title;
                        the 1852 Senate version selected the first three words of the preamble for a
                        main title, i.e., Articles of a treaty; the 1873 <title>Compilation</title>
                        employed <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie</title>; and the 1884
                            <title>Laws</title> chose <title>Fort Laramie Treaty, September 17,
                            1851</title>. Many earlier treaties &#8212; such as those listed in
                        the Index of the first volume of the <title>American State Papers: Indian
                            Affairs</title> volume (1832, pp. lxxii-lxxvi) under a heading of
                        "Treaties made with Indian Tribes" &#8212; used the site of the
                        document's signing as a title component. Thus, <title>Treaty made at Fort
                            Harmar, on 9th January, 1789, with the Six Nations</title> leads off
                        that <title>American State Papers</title> Index summary. While this
                        identification method might have been in fashion at the beginning of the
                        nineteenth century, it was not at the beginning of the twentieth, especially
                        after the creation of the "Names of Indian tribes and bands" list,<ref
                            n="38" target="n38"/> and so Kappler's more tribe-oriented and
                        chronologically clearer title for <title>Fort Laramie</title>, no matter how
                        attenuated by the use of the <term>etc.</term>, has been employed here to
                        gain, rather than to lose, information about the event.</p>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>

                    <p>The <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc., 1851</title> was a key
                        transaction between the federal government and nine major American Indian
                        tribes: the Sioux; the Gros Ventre, Mandan, and Arikara; the Assiniboine;
                        the Blackfoot; the Crow; and the Cheyenne and Arapaho. Its scale &#8212;
                        in terms of lands ceded or of populations of peoples involved<ref n="39"
                            target="n39"/> &#8212; made it one of the most significant events
                        during the entire period of treaty making with America's indigenous peoples.
                        Yet, Kappler confessed that "[b]y inadvertence on the part of the Interior
                        Department, ratification by the tribes was not certified to the State
                        Department and therefore the treaty was not promulgated by the President"
                        (1929, p. 1065). It was then only through the outcomes of the
                            <title>Moore</title> and the <title>Roy</title> proceedings, before the
                        United States Court of Claims, at the start of the twentieth century that
                        this instrument was finally deemed valid.</p>

                    <p>A more appropriate text for it &#8212; <title>
                            <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie09.xml">Laramie09</ref>
                        </title>
                        <!-- (hotlink this)--> &#8212; is now respectfully submitted, as a
                        closer likeness to the actual contract created by those tribes and this
                        nation on 17 September 1851, and through alterations made within the walls
                        of Congress. The textual inaccuracies contained in previous federal
                        compilations, many of which were carried forward for decades, required
                        intervention and correction, primarily because this document remains the law
                        of the land: it defines a treaty between sovereigns. The decision to revert
                        to the original treaty language of <title>Fort Laramie</title> &#8212;
                        captured from digital images of that instrument &#8212; and to then
                        narrowly tune that material only through incorporating the annuity revision,
                        yields a better final content that conveys not only that later Senate
                        mediation, but also, as echoed by their signatures in the Fall of 1851, the
                        words for which <emph>all</emph> tribes gave their assent.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
        <milestone unit="crosses"/>
        <back>
            <div1>
                <head>References</head>

                <bibl><title level="m">A Compilation of All the Treaties Between the United States
                        and the Indian Tribes Now in Force as Laws</title>. (<date value="1873"
                        >1873</date>). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government
                        Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">A statistical view of the Indian nations inhabiting the
                        territory of Louisiana and the countries adjacent to its northern and
                        western boundaries</title>. (<date value="1832">1832</date>). <title
                        level="m">American State Papers: Indian Affairs</title>, vol. 1 (pp.
                    705-743). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Gales and
                        Seaton</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">American State Papers: Indian Affairs</title>, vol. 1. (<date
                        value="1832">1832</date>). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Gales and Seaton</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">An act making appropriations for the support of the Army for
                        the fiscal year ending June thirtieth, 1877, and for other purposes</title>.
                        (<date value="1876">1876</date>). 19 <title level="m">Stat.</title>
                    97.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">An act to amend the act, entitled "An act to provide for the
                        publication of the laws of the United States, and for other
                        purposes."</title> (<date value="1820">1820</date>). 3 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 576.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">An act to establish a court for the investigation of claims
                        against the United States</title>. (<date value="1855">1855</date>). 10
                        <title level="m">Stat.</title> 612.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">An act to ratify and amend an agreement with the Indians of
                        the Crow Reservation in Montana, and making appropriations to carry the same
                        into effect</title>. (<date value="1904">1904</date>). 33 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 352.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Annual reports of the Department of the Interior for the
                        fiscal year ended June 30, 1900. Indian Affairs. Report of Commissioner and
                        appendixes.</title> (<date value="1900">1900</date>). House of
                    Representatives. 56th Congress, 2nd session. House Document No. 5, pt. 2-1
                        (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 4101). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Annual reports of the Department of the Interior for the
                        fiscal year ended June 30, 1901. Indian Affairs. Part I. Report of the
                        Commissioner, and appendixes</title>. (<date value="1901">1901</date>).
                    House of Representatives. 57th Congress, 1st session. House Document No. 5, pt.
                    2-1 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 4290). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Annual reports of the Department of the Interior for the
                        fiscal year ended June 30, 1903. Indian Affairs. Part I. Report of the
                        Commissioner, and appendixes</title>. (<date value="1904">1904</date>).
                    House of Representatives. 58th Congress, 2nd session. House Document No. 5, pt.
                    2-1 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 4645). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Arends, J.</author> and <author>Van den Berg, M.</author> (<date
                        value="2004">2004</date>). <title level="a">The Saramaka peace treaty in
                        Sranan: An edition of the 1762 text (including a copy of the original
                        manuscript)</title>. In <title level="m">Creolica: Revue du Groupe Europen
                        de Recherches en Langues Cr&#233;oles</title>. Accessed on 27 April 2009
                    at <ref n="http://www.creolica.net/saramakaPC"
                        >http://www.creolica.net/saramakaPC</ref>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Articles of a treaty</title>. (<date value="1852"
                    >1852</date>). Senate. 32nd Congress, 1st session. Senate Confidential Executive
                    Document No. 11. <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government
                        Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Aust, A.</author> (<date value="2007">2007</date>). <title level="m"
                        >Modern Treaty Law and Practice</title> (Second edition). <pubPlace>New
                        York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Baird, W. D.</author> (<date value="1979">1979</date>). <title
                        level="a">William A. Jones, 1897-1904</title>. In <editor>R. M.
                        Kvasnicka</editor> and <editor>H. J. Viola</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m"
                        >The Commissioners of Indian Affairs, 1824-1977</title> (pp. 211-220).
                        <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Batten, D.</author> (<date value="2009">2009</date>). <title level="m"
                        >Guide to U. S. Government Publications: 2009 edition</title>. <pubPlace>New
                        York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Gale</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bell, J. B.</author> (<date value="1912">1912</date>). <title
                        level="a">Official Congressional Directory for the use of the United States
                        Congress, 62d Congress, 3d session, beginning December 2, 1912.</title>
                    Senate. 62nd Congress, 3rd session (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 6341).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bernholz, C. D.</author> (<date value="2009">2009</date>). <title
                        level="a">Citation abuse and legal writing: A note on the <title>Treaty of
                            Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc., 1851</title> and 11 <title level="m"
                            >Stat.</title> 749</title>. <title level="j"
                        >Legal Reference Services Quarterly 29</title>, 133-148.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bernholz, C. D.</author> and <author n="">Heidenreich,
                        S.</author> (<date value="2009">2009</date>). <title level="a">Loci sigilli
                        and American Indian treaties: Reflections on the creation of volume 2 of
                        Kappler's <title>Indian Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title></title>. <title
                        level="j">Government Information Quarterly</title> 26, 605-611.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bernholz, C. D.</author> and <author n="">Weiner, R. J.</author>
                        (<date value="2008a">2008a</date>). <title level="a">American Indian
                        treaties in the Courts of Claims: A guide to treaty citations from opinions
                        of the United States Courts of Claims</title>. <title level="j">Government
                        Information Quarterly</title> 25, 313-327.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bernholz, C. D.</author> and <author n="">Weiner, R. J.</author>
                        (<date value="2008b">2008b</date>). <title level="a">The Palmer and Stevens
                        "usual and accustomed places" treaties in the opinions of the
                    courts</title>. <title level="j">Government Information Quarterly</title> 25,
                    778-795.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bernholz, C. D.</author> and <author n="">Weiner, R. J.</author>
                        (<date value="2008c">2008c</date>). <title level="a">The world of Charles J.
                        Kappler: A digital portrait</title>. <title level="j">Legal Reference
                        Services Quarterly</title> 27, 377-383.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bernholz, C. D.</author>, <author n="">Pytlik Zillig, B.
                        L.</author>, and <author n="">Anderson, C. G.</author> (<date value="2008"
                        >2008</date>). <title level="a">The words you brought us: Digital lexicon of
                        the recognized American Indian treaties</title>. <title level="j">Library
                        Collections, Acquisitions, and Technical Services</title> 32,
                    104-106.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Boczek, B. A.</author> (<date value="2005">2005</date>). <title
                        level="m">International Law: A Dictionary</title>. <pubPlace>Lanham,
                        MD</pubPlace>: <publisher>Scarecrow Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Bright, W.</author> (<date value="2004">2004</date>). <title
                        level="a">A glossary of Native American toponyms and ethnonyms from the
                        Lewis and Clark journals</title>. <title level="j">Names</title> 52,
                    163-237.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Bulletin of the Bureau of Rolls and Library, No. 7</title>.
                        (<date value="1895">1895</date>). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Department of State</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Butler, C. H.</author> (<date value="1902">1902</date>). <title
                        level="m">The Treaty-making Power of the United States. Vol. 1. Pt. 1: The
                        United States is a Nation. Pt. 2: Historical Review of the Treaty-making
                        Power of the United States.</title>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Banks Law
                    Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Carter, C. E.</author> (<date value="1934">1934</date>). <title
                        level="m">The Territorial Papers of the United States. Volume II: The
                        Territory Northwest of the River Ohio, 1787-1803</title>.
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Channing, E.</author> (<date value="1921">1921</date>). <title
                        level="m">A History of the United States: Vol. 5 &#8212; The Period of
                        Transition, 1815-1848</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Claims which the Crow Indians may have against the United
                        States</title>. (<date value="1926">1926</date>). Senate. 69th Congress, 1st
                    session. Senate Report No. 352, pt. 1 and 2 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title>
                    8524). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Clark, E. E.</author> (<date value="1966">1966</date>). <title
                        level="m">Indian Legends From the Northern Rockies</title>.
                        <pubPlace>Norman, OK</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Oklahoma
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Cohen, F. S.</author> (<date value="1942">1942</date>). <title
                        level="m">Handbook of Federal Indian Law, with Reference Tables and
                        Index</title>. <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government
                        Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Compilation on Indian Affairs</title>. (<date value="1902"
                        >1902</date>). <title level="j">Congressional Record</title> 35,
                    5664-5665.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Confederated Tribes of Colville Reservation v. United
                        States</title>, 43 Ind. Cl. Comm. 505 (<date value="1978"
                    >1978</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Conferring upon the Court of Claims jurisdiction in cases of
                        claims of the Crow tribe of Indians</title>. (<date value="1926"
                    >1926</date>). House of Representatives. 69th Congress, 1st session. House
                    Report No. 954 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 8533). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Criswell, E. H.</author> (<date value="1940">1940</date>). <title
                        level="a">Lewis and Clark: Linguistic pioneers</title>. <title level="j"
                        >University of Missouri Studies</title> 15, i-102.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Crow Nation or Tribe of Indians of Montana v. United
                        States</title>, 81 Ct. Cl. 238 (<date value="1935">1935</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Crow Tribe of Indians v. United States</title>, 3 Ind. Cl.
                    Comm. 147 (<date value="1954">1954</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Crow Tribe of Indians v. United States</title>, 151 Ct. Cl.
                    281 (<date value="1960">1960</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Deloria, V.</author> and <author n="">DeMallie, R. J.</author>
                        (<date value="1999">1999</date>). <title level="m">Documents of American
                        Indian Diplomacy: Treaties, Agreements, and Conventions, 1775-1979</title>.
                        <pubPlace>Norman, OK</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Oklahoma
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">DeMallie, R. J.</author> (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title
                        level="a">Sioux until 1850</title>. In <editor n="">W. C.
                        Sturtevant</editor> and <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title
                        level="m"> Handbook of North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1:
                        Plains</title> (pp. 718-760). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Smithsonian Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">DeMallie, R. J.</author> and <author n="">Miller, D. R.</author>
                        (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title level="a">Assiniboine</title>. In
                        <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and <editor n="">R. J.
                        DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of North American
                        Indians, vol. 13, part 1: Plains</title> (pp. 572-595).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Dempsey, H. A.</author> (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title
                        level="a">Blackfoot</title>. In <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and
                        <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of
                        North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1: Plains</title> (pp. 604-628).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Dexter, R. W.</author> (<date value="1961">1961</date>). <title
                        level="a">Mussel Shoals vs. Muscle Shoals</title>. <title level="j"
                        >Sterkiana</title> 4, 29-31.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Dexter, R. W.</author> (<date value="1967">1967</date>). <title
                        level="a">Addenda on mussel vs. muscle</title>. <title level="j"
                        >Sterkiana</title> 27, 1-2.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Documents Relating to the Negotiation of Ratified and
                        Unratified Treaties with Various Tribes of Indians, 1801-69</title>. (<date
                        value="1960">1960</date>). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>National Archives and Records Administration</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Eastman, M. H.</author> (<date value="1849">1849</date>). <title
                        level="m">Dahcotah; or, Life and Legends of the Sioux Around Fort
                        Snelling</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>John
                        Wiley</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Fort Snelling investigation</title>. (<date value="1858"
                        >1858</date>). House of Representatives. 35th Congress, 1st session, House
                    Report No. 351 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 965). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Fowler, L.</author> (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title
                        level="a">Arapaho</title>. In <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and
                        <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of
                        North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1: Plains</title> (pp. 840-862).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl>Fowler, L. and Flannery, R. (2001). Gros Ventre. In <editor n="">W. C.
                        Sturtevant</editor> and <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title
                        level="m">Handbook of North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1:
                        Plains</title> (pp. 677-694). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Smithsonian Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Gallatin, A.</author> (<date value="1836">1836</date>). <title
                        level="a">A synopsis of the Indian tribes within the United States east of
                        the Rocky Mountains and in the British and Russian possessions</title>.
                        <title level="j">Archaeologia Americana</title> 2, 1-422.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Godfrey v. Iowa Land &amp; Trust Co.</title>, 21 Okla.
                    293 (<date value="1908">1908</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Great Indian Council of the Plains</title>. (<date
                        value="1851">1851, October 4</date>). <title level="j">North American and
                        United States Gazette</title>, col. I.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hafen, L. R.</author> and <author n="">Young, F. M.</author>
                        (<date value="1938">1938</date>). <title level="m">Fort Laramie and the
                        Pageant of the West, 1834-1890</title>. <pubPlace>Glendale, CA</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Arthur H. Clark</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hill, E. E.</author> (<date value="1974">1974</date>). <title
                        level="m">The Office of Indian Affairs, 1824-1880: Historical
                        Sketches</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clearwater
                        Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hodge, F. W.</author> (<date value="1907a">1907a</date>). <title
                        level="m">Handbook of American Indians North of Mexico</title>. House of
                    Representatives. 59th Congress, 1st session. House Document No. 926, pt. 1
                        (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 5001). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hodge, F. W.</author> (<date value="1907b">1907b</date>). <title
                        level="m">Handbook of American Indians North of Mexico</title>. House of
                    Representatives. 59th Congress, 1st session. House Document No. 926, pt. 2
                        (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 5002). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hoig, S.</author> (<date value="2006">2006</date>). <title
                        level="m">White Man's Paper Trail: Grand Councils and Treaty-making on the
                        Central Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>University Press of Colorado</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hoxie, F. E.</author> (<date value="1995">1995</date>). <title
                        level="m">Parading Through History: The Making of the Crow Nation in
                        America, 1805-1935</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Hunt, G.</author> (<date value="1914">1914</date>). <title
                        level="m">The Department of State of the United States: Its History and
                        Functions</title>. <pubPlace>New Haven, CT</pubPlace>: <publisher>Yale
                        University Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Indian Treaties, and Laws and Regulations Relating to Indian
                        Affairs</title>. (<date value="1826">1826</date>). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Way &amp; Gideon</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Isom, B. G.</author> (<date value="1972">1972</date>). <title
                        level="a">A biologist's look at the history of Muscle Shoals (Mussel
                        Shoals)</title>. <title level="j">Malacological Review</title> 4,
                    203-206.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Jones, E.</author> (<date value="1966">1966</date>). <title
                        level="m">Citadel in the Wilderness: The Story of Fort Snelling and the Old
                        Northwest Frontier</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Coward-McCann</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Journal of the Executive Proceedings of the Senate of the United States of America</title>. (<date value="1828">1828</date>).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Duff Green</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Journal of the Senate of the United States of America, being
                        the first session of the Thirty-second Congress; begun and held in the City
                        of Washington, December 1, 1851, in the seventy-sixth year of the
                        independence of the United States.</title> (<date value="1852">1852</date>).
                    Senate. 32nd Congress, 1st session (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 610).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1903a">1903a</date>). <title
                        level="a">Indian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 1. Statutes, executive
                        orders, proclamations, and statistics of tribes</title>. Senate. 57th
                    Congress, 1st session. Senate Document No. 452, pt. 1 (<title level="m">Serial
                        Set</title> 4253). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1903b">1903b</date>). I<title
                        level="a">ndian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 2. Treaties. Senate. 57th
                        Congress, 1st session</title>. Senate Document No. 452, pt. 2 (<title
                        level="m">Serial Set</title> 4254). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1904a">1904a</date>). <title
                        level="a">Indian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 1. Laws. Senate. 58th
                        Congress, 2nd session</title>. Senate Document No. 319, pt. 1 (<title
                        level="m">Serial Set</title> 4623). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1904b">1904b</date>). <title
                        level="a">Indian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 2. Treaties. Senate. 58th
                        Congress, 2nd session</title>. Senate Document No. 319, pt. 2 (<title
                        level="m">Serial Set</title> 4624). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1913">1913</date>). <title
                        level="a">Indian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 3. Laws. Senate. 62nd
                        Congress, 2nd session</title>. Senate Document No. 719 (<title level="m"
                        >Serial Set</title> 6166). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1929">1929</date>). <title
                        level="a">Indian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 4. Laws. Senate. 70th
                        Congress, 1st session</title>. Senate Document No. 53 (<title level="m"
                        >Serial Set</title> 8849). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1941">1941</date>). <title
                        level="a">Indian affairs. Laws and treaties, vol. 5. Laws. Senate. 76th
                        Congress, 3rd session</title>. Senate Document No. 194 (<title level="m"
                        >Serial Set</title> 10458). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1972a">1972a</date>). <title
                        level="m">Indian Treaties: 1778-1883</title>. <pubPlace>Mattituck,
                        NY</pubPlace>: <publisher>Amereon House</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1972b">1972b</date>). <title
                        level="m">Indian Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title>, vol. 1-5. <pubPlace>New
                        York</pubPlace>: <publisher>AMS Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1973">1973</date>). <title
                        level="m">Indian Treaties: 1778-1883</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Interland Publishing</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author>Kappler, C. J.</author> (<date value="1975">1975</date>). <title
                        level="m">Indian Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title>, vol. 1-5.
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Kelly, L. C.</author> (<date value="1979">1979</date>). <title
                        level="a">Charles Henry Burke, 1921-29</title>. In <editor n="">R. M.
                        Kvasnicka</editor> and <editor n="">H. J. Viola</editor> (Eds.). <title
                        level="m">The Commissioners of Indian Affairs, 1824-1977</title> (pp.
                    251-261). <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Kvasnicka, R. M.</author> (<date value="1979">1979</date>).
                        <title level="a">George W. Manypenny, 1853-57</title>. In <editor n="">R. M.
                        Kvasnicka</editor> and <editor n="">H. J. Viola</editor> (Eds.). T<title
                        level="m">he Commissioners of Indian Affairs, 1824-1977</title> (pp. 57-67).
                        <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Laws of the United States Relating to Indian Affairs:
                        Compiled from the Revised Statutes of the United States enacted June 22,
                        1874, and from Statutes at Large from that date to March 4, 1883: Also,
                        Special Acts and Resolutions Previous to the Enactment of the Revised
                        Statutes, not Embraced in or Repealed by the Revision: Also, List of all
                        Ratified Treaties and Agreements Made with the Several Indian Tribes</title>
                    (3rd ed.). (<date value="1884">1884</date>). <pubPlace>Washington,
                    DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Lessoff, A.</author> (<date value="1999">1999</date>). <title
                        level="a">William Morris Stewart</title>. In <editor n="">J. A.
                        Garraty</editor> and <editor n="">M. C. Carnes</editor> (Eds.). <title
                        level="m">American National Biography</title>, vol. 20 (pp. 755-757).
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oxford University
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Malouf, C. I.</author> (<date value="1998">1998</date>). <title
                        level="a">Flathead and Pend d'Oreille</title>. In <editor n="">W. C.
                        Sturtevant</editor> and <editor n="">D. E. Walker</editor> (Eds.). <title
                        level="m">Handbook of North American Indians</title>, vol. 12: Plateau (pp.
                    297-312). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Matthes, G. H.</author> (<date value="1925">1925</date>). M<title
                        level="a">uscle Shoals vs. Mussel Shoals</title>. <title level="j"
                        >Science</title> 61, 209.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Message from the President of the United States</title>.
                        (<date value="1853">1853</date>). Senate. 33rd Congress, 1st session. Senate
                    Executive Document No. 1, pt. 1 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 690).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Merrion v. Jicarilla Apache Tribe</title>, 455 U.S. 130
                        (<date value="1982">1982</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Montana v. United States</title>, 450 U.S. 544 (<date
                        value="1981">1981</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Moore v. United States</title>, 32 Ct. Cl. 593 (<date
                        value="1897">1897</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Moore, J. M.</author>, <author n="">Liberty, M. P.</author>, and
                        <author n="">Straus, A. T.</author> (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title
                        level="a">Cheyenne</title>. In <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and
                        <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of
                        North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1: Plains</title> (pp. 863-885).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><editor n="">Moulton, G. E.</editor> (Ed.). (<date value="1987a"
                    >1987a</date>). <title level="m">The Journals of the Lewis &amp; Clark
                        Expedition. Volume 3, August 25, 1804-April 6, 1805.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><editor n="">Moulton, G. E.</editor> (Ed.). (<date value="1987b"
                    >1987b</date>). <title level="m">The Journals of the Lewis &amp; Clark
                        Expedition. Volume 4, April 7-July 27, 1805.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><editor n="">Moulton, G. E.</editor> (Ed.). (<date value="1988">1988</date>).
                        <title level="m">The Journals of the Lewis &amp; Clark Expedition.
                        Volume 5, July 28-November 1, 1805.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Musselshell River, Mont.</title> (<date value="1931"
                        >1931</date>). House of Representatives. 72nd Congress, 1st session. House
                    Document No. 146 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 9553).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Navajo Tribe of Indians v. United States</title>, 9 Cl. Ct.
                    336 (<date value="1986">1986</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Newton, N. J.</author> (<date value="2005">2005</date>). <title
                        level="m">Felix S. Cohen's Federal Indian Law</title>. <pubPlace>Newark,
                        NJ</pubPlace>: <publisher>LexisNexis/Matthew Bender</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Nichols, F. S.</author> (<date value="1954">1954</date>). <title
                        level="m">Index to Schoolcraft's "Indian Tribes of the United
                        States."</title> Smithsonian Institution. Bureau of American Ethnology
                    Bulletin 152. <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government
                        Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Northwestern Bands of Shoshone Indians v. United
                        States</title>, 324 U.S. 335 (<date value="1945">1945</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Oneida Nation of New York v. United States</title>, 25 Ind.
                    Cl. Comm. 583 (<date value="1971">1971</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Parks, D. R.</author> (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title
                        level="a">Arikara</title>. In <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and
                        <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of
                        North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1: Plains</title> (pp. 365-390).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Price, R.</author> (<date value="1983a">1983a</date>). <title
                        level="m">First-time: The Historical Vision of an Afro-American
                        People</title>. <pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>: <publisher>Johns Hopkins
                        University Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Price, R.</author> (<date value="1983b">1983b</date>). <title
                        level="m">To Slay the Hydra: Dutch Colonial Perspectives on the Saramaka
                        Wars</title>. <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI</pubPlace>: <publisher>Karoma
                        Publishers</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Plischke, E.</author> (<date value="1999">1999</date>). <title
                        level="m">U. S. Department of State: A Reference History</title>.
                        <pubPlace>Westport, CT</pubPlace>: <publisher>Greenwood
                    Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Prucha, F. P.</author> (<date value="1994">1994</date>). <title
                        level="m">American Indian Treaties: The History of a Political
                        Anomaly</title>. <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of
                        California Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Putney, D. T.</author> (<date value="1979">1979</date>). <title
                        level="a">Robert Grosvenor Valentine, 1909-12</title>. In <editor n="">R. M.
                        Kvasnicka</editor> and <editor n="">H. J. Viola</editor> (Eds.). <title
                        level="m">The Commissioners of Indian Affairs, 1824-1977</title> (pp.
                    233-242). <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska
                        Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Reports of the Department of the Interior for the fiscal year
                        ended June 30 1918, vol. II: Indian Affairs. Territories.</title> (<date
                        value="1919">1919</date>). House of Representatives. 65th Congress, 3rd
                    session. House Document No. 1544, pt. 2 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title>
                    7498). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Ritter, R. M.</author> (<date value="2003">2003</date>). <title
                        level="m">The Oxford Style Manual</title>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Roberts, R. B.</author> (<date value="1988">1988</date>). <title
                        level="m">Encyclopedia of Historic Forts: The Military, Pioneer, and Trading
                        Posts of the United States</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Macmillan Publishing Co.</publisher></bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Roy v. United States and the Ogallala Tribe of Sioux
                        Indians</title>, 45 Ct. Cl. 177 (<date value="1910">1910</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Royce, C. C.</author> (<date value="1899">1899</date>). <title
                        level="m">Indian Land Cessions in the United States</title>. 18th Annual
                    Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian
                    Institution, 1896-97, Part 2. House of Representatives. 56th Congress, 1st
                    session. House Document No. 736 (<title level="m">Serial Set</title> 4015) (pp.
                    521-997). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing
                        Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">St. Germaine v. Circuit Court for Vilas County</title>, 938
                    F.2d 75 (<date value="1991">1991</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Schoolcraft, H. R.</author> (<date value="1852"
                    >1852-1857</date>). <title level="m">Information Respecting the History,
                        Condition and Prospects of the Indian Tribes of the United States</title>.
                        <pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Lippincott, Grambo
                        &amp; Co.</publisher></bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Second report of the United States Board on Geographic
                        Names</title>. (<date value="1900">1900</date>). House of Representatives.
                    56th Congress, 1st session. House Document No. 472 (<title level="m">Serial
                        Set</title> 3988). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Sioux Tribe v. United States</title>, 21 Ind. Cl. Comm. 371
                        (<date value="1969">1969</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Sioux Tribe of Indians v. United States</title>, 15 Ind. Cl.
                    Comm. 577 (<date value="1969">1969</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Sioux Tribe of Indians v. United States</title>, 205 Ct. Cl.
                    148 (<date value="1974">1974</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Sixth Report of the United States Geographic Board: 1890 to
                        1932</title>. (<date value="1933">1933</date>). <pubPlace>Washington,
                        DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Smith, B. M.</author> (<date value="1986">1986</date>). <title
                        level="a">Politics and the Crow Indian land cessions</title>. <title
                        level="j">Montana: The Magazine of Western History</title> 36, 24-37.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Strickland, R.</author> (<date value="1982">1982</date>). <title
                        level="m">Felix S. Cohen's Handbook of Federal Indian Law</title> (1982
                    ed.). <pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace>:
                    <publisher>Michie</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Swanton, J. R.</author> (<date value="1952">1952</date>). <title
                        level="m">The Indian Tribes of North America</title>. House of
                    Representatives. 81st Congress, 2nd session. House Document No. 383 (<title
                        level="m">Serial Set</title> 11,475). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">The Confederated Tribes of the Warm Springs Reservation of
                        Oregon v. United States</title>, 12 Ind. Cl. Comm. 664 (<date value="1963"
                        >1963</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">The Oxford English Dictionary</title> (Second edition).
                        (<date value="1989">1989</date>). <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Three Affiliated Tribes et al v. United States</title>, 25
                    Ind. Cl. Comm. 179 (<date value="1971">1971</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="a">Travel expenses, officers, and employees, Department of the
                        Interior</title>. (<date value="1919">1919</date>). House of
                    Representatives. 66th Congress, 2nd session. House Document No. 442 (<title
                        level="m">Serial Set</title> 7769). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Treaties Between the United States of America and the Several
                        Indian Tribes, From 1778 to 1837</title>. (<date value="1837">1837</date>).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Langtree and
                        O'Sullivan</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">United States v. Finch</title>, 548 F.2d 822 (<date
                        value="1976">1976</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">United States v. Northern Pacific Railway Co.</title>, 311
                    U.S. 317 (<date value="1940">1940</date>).</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Van Tyne, C. H.</author> and <author n="">Leland, W. G.</author>
                        (<date value="1904">1904</date>). <title level="m">Guide to the Archives of
                        the Government of the United States in Washington</title>.
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Carnegie
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Voget, F. W.</author> (<date value="2001">2001</date>). <title
                        level="a">Crow</title>. In <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and
                        <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of
                        North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1: Plains</title> (pp. 695-717).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Walker, D. E.</author> (<date value="1998">1998</date>). <title
                        level="a">Nez Perce</title>. In <editor n="">W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and
                        <editor n="">D. E. Walker</editor> (Eds.). <title level="m">Handbook of
                        North American Indians, vol. 12: Plateau</title> (pp. 420-438).
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>: <publisher>Smithsonian
                        Institution</publisher>. </bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">West, C. V.</author> (<date value="1993">1993</date>). <title
                        level="m">Capitalism on the Frontier: Billings and the Yellowstone Valley in
                        the Nineteenth Century</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln, NE</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><author n="">Wood, W. R.</author> and <author n="">Irwin, L.</author> (<date
                        value="2001">2001</date>). <title level="a">Mandan</title>. In <editor n=""
                        >W. C. Sturtevant</editor> and <editor n="">R. J. DeMallie</editor> (Eds.).
                        <title level="m">Handbook of North American Indians, vol. 13, part 1:
                        Plains</title> (pp. 349-364). <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Smithsonian Institution</publisher>.</bibl>

                <bibl><title level="m">Yankton Sioux v. the United States</title>, 97 Ct. Cl. 56
                        (<date value="1942">1942</date>).</bibl>
            </div1>

            <div1>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>We were aided during this investigation by a number of colleagues, and would like
                    to express our gratitude to Sara Berndt at George Washington University; Jane
                    Fitzgerald at the National Archives and Records Administration; and Brent Baum,
                    Karin Dalziel, Katie Heupel, Vicki Martin, and Laura Weakly at the Center for
                    Digital Research in the Humanities at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.</p>

<p>Several of our questions were addressed by Errapel Mejias-Vicandi at the Department of Modern Languages and Literatures at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, and by Stephan G. Custer and William K. Wyckoff of the Department of Earth Sciences at Montana State University; we are grateful for this assistance.</p>
            </div1>

            <milestone unit="crosses"/>

            <div1><anchor id="appendix"/>
                <head>Appendix</head>
               

                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie51.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie51</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                            <lb/><lb/>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie52.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie52</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                            <lb/><lb/>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie73.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie73</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                            <lb/><lb/>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie84.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie84</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie03.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie03</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                            <lb/><lb/>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie04.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie04</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                            <lb/><lb/>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie29.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie29</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                            <lb/><lb/>
                            <title>
                                <ref n="treaty.tfl.laramie09.xml"  type="newwindow"><hi rend="bold">Laramie09</hi></ref>
                            </title>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    </table>

                <figure n="table">
                    <head/>
                    <p><hi rend="bold"><ref
                        n="Table1-LED.pdf"  type="newwindow">Table I</ref></hi> <!-- Aligned text elements of the seven federal versions of
                        the <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc., 1851</title>, for the years 1851
                        through 1929, and of the proposed corrected rendition. --></p>
                    <figDesc/>
                </figure>

                <figure n="table">
                    <head/>
                    <p><hi rend="bold"><ref
                        n="Table2-LED.pdf" type="newwindow">Table II</ref></hi> <!-- Tribe names found in the preambles and in Article 5 of
                        the seven federal versions of the <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with Sioux, etc.,
                        1851</title>, for the years 1851 through 1929, accompanied by comparative spellings
                        found in the "Names of Indian tribes and bands" (NIT&amp;B) list
                        proposed by the Office of Indian Affairs in conjunction with the Bureau of
                        Ethnology (Kappler, 1904a, p. 1021). --></p>
                    <figDesc/>
                </figure>

            </div1>
            
            <milestone unit="crosses"/>

            <div1>
                <note id="f01">* Phone: 402-472-4473<lb/> Fax: 402-472-5181<lb/> E-mail:
                    cbernholz2@unl.edu</note>
                <note id="f02">** Phone: 402-472-4547<lb/> Fax: 402-472-5181<lb/> E-mail:
                    bzillig1@unl.edu</note>
                <note id="n01">1. This statement may be found in the first volume of the <title>Journal
                        of the Executive Proceedings of the Senate of the United States of
                        America</title> (1828, p. 26).</note>
                <note id="n02">2. Subsequently, however, treaty making with the tribes concluded on 3
                    March 1871 (16 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 544, 566). In his classic
                    presentation on the Department of State, Hunt (1914, p. 396) declared that
                    "Indian treaties, it should be remarked, of which formerly many were made, were
                    never negotiated by the Secretary of State, but by special commissioners acting
                    for the President under the War Department, which had control of Indian affairs
                    until the Department of the Interior took over the business." As will be seen in
                    the following discussion, the pertinent <title>Treaty of Fort Laramie with
                        Sioux, etc., 1851</title> dialogue was administered by "Commissioners
                    specially appointed and authorized by the President of the United States"
                    (Articles of a treaty, 1852, p. 1).</note>
                <note id="n03">3. The nine tribes involved in this transaction are a substantial
                    cross-section of Indians in the northern Plains in the mid-nineteenth century.
                    The <title>Handbook of North American Indians</title> is a useful resource for
                    an overview of these groups, their names ordered here as they were in the treaty
                    itself: Sioux (DeMallie, 2001); Cheyenne (Moore, Liberty, and Straus, 2001);
                    Arapaho (Fowler, 2001); Crow (Voget, 2001); Assiniboine (DeMallie and Miller,
                    2001); Gros Ventre (Fowler and Flannery, 2001); Mandan (Wood and Irwin, 2001);
                    Arikara (Parks, 2001); and the absent but still affected Blackfoot (Dempsey,
                    2001). These chapters furnished the tribe spellings used for material written as
                    part of this article, while appellations referenced in examined documents were
                    reproduced as published, e.g., <term>Arickarees</term>, <term>Blackfeet</term>,
                        <term>Gros Ventres</term>, and <term>Mandans</term>. Cited documents,
                    related to Kappler's <title>
                        Indian Affairs: Laws and Treaties</title> compilation, may be
                    accessed through the <ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/">Oklahoma State University's Web site</ref>. <title>Fort Laramie</title> is also
                    available at <ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/sio0594.htm">
                        Oklahoma State</ref>.</note>
                <note id="n04">4. Lessoff (1999) presents a brief biography of Stewart.</note>
                <note id="n05">5. Bernholz and Weiner (2008c), and the described Web site therein, have
                    more on the life of Charles J. Kappler.</note>
                <note id="n06">6. Later, three additional volumes were developed: Senate Document No.
                    719; Senate Document No. 53; and Senate Document No. 194 (Kappler, 1913, 1929,
                    and 1941, respectively) with germane contemporary federal Indian law materials.
                    All five volumes were reoffered thirty years later by the federal government
                    (1975). Commercial publishers created similar sets (1972b), with special focus
                    placed on the 1904 <title>Treaties</title> tome (1972a and 1973).</note>
                <note id="n07">7. Hill's volume observed that the term "'Office of Indian Affairs' was
                    the name commonly used until 1947" for this section of the earlier Department of
                    War and then, after 1849, of the Department of the Interior (1974, p. 1).</note>
                <note id="n08">8. A Congressional resolution in June 1790 assured "[t]hat all treaties
                    made, or which shall be made and promulgated, under the authority of the United
                    States, shall, from time to time, be published and annexed to their code of
                    laws, by the Secretary of State" (1 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 187). Each
                    such law was "registered in the Bureau of Rolls and Library and a printed copy
                    of it, which the Department has already received before it was finally approved,
                    is then compared with it" for verification (Hunt, 1914, p. 279). The
                        <title>Guide to U. S. Government Publications</title> (Batten, 2009, p. 699)
                    presents 1789 to 1921 as the operational years of the Bureau of Rolls and
                    Library; it was reorganized in May 1921 (Plischke, 1999, p. 370).</note>
                <note id="n09">9. See Bernholz (2009) for a discussion of this 11 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 749 citation misuse.</note>
                <note id="n10">10. The spelling errors extend to geographical names as well. Moulton
                    (1987b, p. 170) included a journal entry of Captain Meriwether Lewis for 20 May
                    1805 that spoke of this "stream we take to be that called by the Minnetares the
                    [blank] or Muscleshell River." A footnote declared that the "Musselshell River.
                    . . still bears the name the captains gave it, translating the Hidatsa name" (p.
                    175, n. 3). Swanton (1952, p. 275) confirmed the interchangeability of
                    Minnetares (now Minitari) and Hidatsa for tribe identification. In the Annual
                    Report of the Commissioner of Indian Affairs for 1853, three letters &#8212;
                    dated 8, 9, and 21 September 1853 &#8212; by Isaac A. Stevens, serving as
                    the Governor of Washington Territory and as part of the Northern Pacific
                    Railroad Exploration and Survey, referenced this river. The first letter
                    contained instructions to Lieutenant Mullan: "Dear Sir: With a select party,
                    consisting of the Pegan guide, the White Crane, Mr. Rose, Mr. Bur, and two
                    voyageurs, you will visit the Flathead camp on the <term>Muscle Shell</term> river" (Message
                    from the President, 1853, p. 462; emphasis added). The other two transmissions,
                    to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, George W. Manypenny (see Kvasnicka, 1979)
                    on the subject of negotiating treaties with the tribes in the Pacific Northwest,
                    remarked first that "Lieutenant Mullan, of the army, starts to-day, with a small
                    detached party to the Flathead camp, on the <term>Muscle Shell</term> river" (p. 461;
                    emphasis added), and second that "I enclose copies of my instructions to
                    Lieutenant Mullan, directing him to visit the Flathead camp, on the <emph>Muscle
                        Shell</emph> river" (p. 460; emphasis added). This suggests that the
                    original spelling was still considered correct at the time of <title>Fort Laramie</title>. The
                    title today is the <emph>Musselshell River</emph>. The waterway, the county, and
                    a town share the same name, north of Billings, Montana, a city founded three
                    decades after <title>Fort Laramie</title> was signed. Roberts (1988, pp.
                    477-478) observed that Montana's Fort Sheridan (1870-1874) evolved from Fort
                    Musselshell (1868-1870), a trading post in that town. He stated that "As a
                    freighting town and trading post, the town of Musselshell also proved a failure"
                    and that "[i]n August 1870 the Montana Hide &amp; Fur Company closed its
                    affairs there and abandoned its warehouse and trading post." A letter from the
                    Secretary of War in 1931 referred to the original installation (Musselshell
                    River, Mont., 1931, p. 10), but the 2000 Census indicated a population of just
                    60. A similar spelling controversy has surrounded the naming of Alabama's Muscle
                    Shoals (Matthes, 1925; Dexter, 1961 and 1967; and Isom, 1972). The United States
                    Board on Geographic Names even went so far as to specify Muscle Shoals as a
                    "series of rapids in Tennessee river, south border of Lauderdale county, Ala.
                    (<emph>Not Mussel Shoals</emph>)" (see Second report of the United States Board
                    on Geographic Names, 1900, p. 92; emphasis added). On facing pages of their
                    superseding sixth report, the Board certified <emph>Muscle Shoals</emph> and
                        <emph>Musselshell</emph> as those rapids and as the river in Montana,
                    respectively. The latter was followed, two entries later, with the directive
                        "<emph>Mussel Shoals</emph>: see Muscle Shoals" (<title>Sixth Report of the
                        United States Geographic Board: 1890 to 1932</title>, 1933, pp. 538-539).
                    Dexter (1961) supplied other muscle/mussel geographic examples.</note>
                <note id="n11">11. This accumulation of cases, from a <title>LexisNexis Academic</title>
                    inquiry, was accomplished through employing the document's "11 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 749" <title>Statutes at Large</title> reference as the search
                    element.</note>
                <note id="n12">12. Absent, however, from Channing's list was <title>A Compilation of All
                        the Treaties Between the United States and the Indian Tribes Now in Force as
                        Laws</title> (1873). Butler (1902), in his important publication <title>The
                        Treaty-making Power of the United States</title>, listed <title>A
                        Compilation of All the Treaties and Laws of the United States Relating to
                        Indian Affairs</title> as part of his "Table of Authorities" (p.
                    xxxii).</note>
                <note id="n13">13. Carter's footnote data are instructive. For the 1789 matter, he
                    stated "the present text, derived from the original treaty sources in the
                    Department of State, reveals a large number of variations from the versions
                    hitherto printed. Although there are no important word differences, the number
                    of punctuation discrepancies in the <title>Statues</title> version, which is followed by
                    Kappler, amount to over 170. In these two versions more than 60 marks of
                    punctuation found in the original treaty are omitted, more than 60 new points
                    are inserted, and over 40 original punctuation marks are altered, many of which
                    changes tend to obscure the sense" (p. 174). The remark for the later treaty
                    declared that "A comparison of the original treaty with the printed texts
                    reveals numerous discrepancies; errors most frequently found relate to
                    punctuation marks &#8212; an actual count in the case of the
                        <title>Statutes</title> version, which is followed by Kappler, revealing
                    more than one hundred changes" (p. 525).</note>
                <note id="n14">14. Father Prucha also supplied an appendix entitled "Treaty documents
                    and their promulgation" that illuminated the legislative process for these
                    materials, including a special section on the 1851 <title>Fort Laramie</title>
                    instrument (Prucha, 1994, pp. 429-445).</note>
                <note id="n15">15. The 150-page disparity evident here for these instruments in the
                    first and the second edition of <title>Treaties</title> is one immediate
                    indication of the extra length generated by the addition of the signatory lists
                    to the latter edition of <title>Treaties</title>.</note>
                <note id="n16">16. A similar outcome in the later <title>Roy v. United States and the
                        Ogallala Tribe of Sioux Indians</title> proceedings (1910) added weight to
                    the discussion surrounding this confirmation; Kappler's entry in volume 4
                    incorporated this subsequent Court of Claims decision (1929, pp.
                    1050-1081).</note>
                <note id="n17">17. This latter document is the <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/yan0776.htm">
                        Treaty with the Yankton Sioux,
                        1858</ref></title> (Kappler, 1904b, pp. 776-781)
                    in which the annuity rights from the earlier <title>Fort Laramie</title> accord were discussed
                    in Articles 1 and 14. These two Articles read, respectively: "They, also, hereby
                    relinquish and abandon all claims and complaints about or growing out of any and
                    all treaties heretofore made by them or other Indians, except their annuity
                    rights under the treaty of Laramie, of September 17, A. D. 1851" (p. 776), and
                    "The said Yanctons do hereby fully acquit and release the United States from all
                    demands against them on the part of said tribe, or any individual thereof,
                    except the beforementioned right of the Yanctons to receive an annuity under
                    said treaty of Laramie, and except, also, such as are herein stipulated and
                    provided for" (p. 780). The 1851 outcome was also cited in Article 3 of the
                        <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/bla0736.htm">
                        Treaty with the Blackfeet, 1855</ref></title> (pp. 736-740):
                    "The Blackfoot Nation consent and agree that all that portion of the country
                    recognized and defined by the treaty of Laramie as Blackfoot territory, lying
                    within lines drawn from the Hell Gate or Medicine Rock Passes in the main range
                    of the Rocky Mountains, in an easterly direction to the nearest source of the
                    Muscle Shell River, thence to. . ." (p. 736).</note>
                <note id="n18">18. Kappler's adherence to an <emph>unratified</emph> status for these
                    negotiations is echoed in the Index for volume 2, but only in the entry for the
                    Sioux: "September 17, 1851, at Fort Laramie (unratified)" (1904b, p.
                    1093).</note>
                <note id="n19">19. Vaughan was part of the Upper Missouri Agency, appointed Agent on 18
                    April 1853 (Hill, 1974, pp. 184-187). The use of the term "Arrickeras" in
                        <title>Fort Laramie</title> in each of his 1903, 1904, and 1904
                    presentations suggests that Kappler adhered to the name found only in the
                    original document, or in the Senate reproduction under consideration during
                    ratification.</note>
                <note id="n20">20. Layne appeared in four <title level="m">Serial Set</title> entries in
                    1910, identified as the "Acting Chief" of the Land Division of the Department of
                    the Interior, the unit designed to handle "all matters pertaining to enrollment,
                    allotment, and sale of lands and property of the Five Civilized Tribes, having
                    charge of all records thereof" (Reports of the Department of the Interior, 1919,
                    p. 424).</note>
                <note id="n21">21. This memo appeared in a House Report as well, dated a month after the
                    Senate document (Conferring upon the Court of Claims jurisdiction in cases of
                    claims of the Crow tribe of Indians, 1926, pp. 2-4).</note>
                <note id="n22">22. <title>Crow Nation or Tribe of Indians of Montana v. United
                        States</title> specifically challenged the taking of lands from the
                    so-called River Crow, who lost these lands that had been acknowledged in
                        <title>Fort Laramie</title> as the result of the subsequent <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/cro1008.htm">
                        Treaty
                        with the Crows, 1868</ref></title> (Kappler, 1904b, pp. 1008-1011).
                    After Kappler's death in 1946, the Crow appeared before the Indian Claims
                    Commission (<title>Crow Tribe of Indians v. United States</title>, 1954), which
                    found for the tribe. A subsequent appeal by the tribe disputing the compensation
                    due summarized the case by stating that "the Crow Tribe of Indians was entitled
                    to recover additional compensation for 30,530,764.8 acres of land, situated in
                    what is now south central Montana and north central Wyoming, which the Tribe
                    ceded to the United States by the Treaty of May 7, 1868, 15 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 649. In its petition to the Commission, the Tribe alleged
                    that prior to the date of that treaty it owned 38,531,174 acres, and that by the
                    Treaty of 1868 it ceded all of its lands, except for a reservation containing
                    8,000,409.2 acres, to the United States for an inadequate and unconscionable
                    consideration" (Crow Tribe of Indians v. United States, 1960, p. 283). This
                    appeal, before the Court of Claims, concluded that "[t]he Crow Tribe was
                    entitled to receive $12,212,305 for its lands. It received $1,111,768.07, so it
                    is entitled to the difference, in the amount of $11,100,536.93. The parties
                    stipulated that the Government was entitled to counterclaims and offsets
                    totaling $857,552.23, so the amount of judgment should be $10,242,984.70" (pp.
                    301-302). See West (1993, p. 42) for a description of the original 38.5 million
                    acre Crow reservation, and the map in Smith (1986, p. 27) of the endless cession
                    of these lands in 1868, 1882, 1891, and 1904. The final transfer, for a total
                    consideration of $1,150,000 and dispensed as stipulated in <title>An act to
                        ratify and amend an agreement with the Indians of the Crow Reservation in
                        Montana, and making appropriations to carry the same into effect</title>
                    (1904), ended a half-century of fruitless Crow efforts to make lasting peace
                    with the federal government.</note>
                <note id="n23">23. The fourth volume's text for <title>Fort Laramie</title> was quoted
                    in <title>United States v. Northern Pacific Railway Co.</title> (1940),
                        <title>Yankton Sioux v. the United States</title> (1942), and <title>Crow
                        Tribe of Indians v. United States</title> (1960).</note>
                <note id="n24">24. There is further confusion induced here. The <title>Statutes</title>'
                    "List of the treaties published in this volume" (facing 9 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 815) has "With the Pottowatamies" instead of ". . .with the
                    Pottowautomie" on the treaty's initial page (9 <title level="m">Stat.</title>
                    853). Hodge (1907b, pp. 291-293) furnished more than one hundred spellings for
                    this tribe; Nichols (1954, p. 188) lists nine alternatives used by Henry Rowe
                    Schoolcraft in his publication on the tribes (1852-1857).</note>
                <note id="n25">25. This allegiance to the accepted text of the <title>Statutes</title>
                    is a demonstration of Kappler's conservative approach, given his history as a
                    federal employee prior to collating <title>Indian Affairs</title>; his
                    relatively new law degree (he graduated from the Law School at Georgetown
                    University with his LL.B degree in 1896 and LL.M the following year; see <ref
                        n="http://kappler.unl.edu">http://kappler.unl.edu</ref>); and the fact that
                        <title>Indian Affairs</title> was created at the specific request of
                    Congress. In the same Preface, he openly stated that "The general form of the
                    Statutes at Large has been followed, as being familiar to publicists and lawyers
                    and best suited to meet practical requirements." Taken together, these points
                    suggest, quite reasonably, that if <title>Fort Laramie</title> had been
                    published in the <title>Statutes</title>, then Kappler would have in all
                    likelihood replicated that primary text, and that in doing so, the original
                    spellings at the time of the transaction would have been used in his 1903 and
                    1904 <title>Treaties</title> texts for this document, even if those appellations
                    were different from the parallel tribal name offered in his Revised Spelling of
                    Indian Names list that mirrored the Office of Indian Affairs' "Names of Indian
                    tribes and bands" one. Therefore, the original tribal spellings, among those
                    found in the rest of the original 1851 text segments, are maintained here, just
                    as Kappler had deployed the array of Potawatomi &#8212; and other
                    &#8212; variants published in the <title>Statutes</title>.</note>
                <note id="n26">26. Indeed, while not catastrophic to either the letter or the spirit of
                    the law, this variability might be considered in part as an index to the
                    background error rate inherent to reproducing such materials in the last half of
                    the nineteenth century.</note>
                <note id="n27">27. Cullen later participated in this role at the <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/win0790.htm">
                        Treaty with the
                        Winnebago, 1859</ref></title> (Kappler, 1904b, pp. 790-792)
                    and as a Commissioner for the <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol5/html_files/v5p0707.html">
                        Treaty with Shoshones, Bannacks, and
                        Sheepeaters, September 24, 1888</ref></title> (Kappler, 1941, pp. 707-708);
                    the latter dealing was left unratified. He was also involved with <title>Fort
                        Laramie</title> entities in other unresolved discussions: the
                        <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol3/HTML_files/IND0714.html#IND0714">
                        Agreement with the River Crow Tribe of Indians, 1868</ref></title>
                    (Kappler, 1913, pp. 714-716)
                    and the <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol4/html_files/v4p1138.html">
                        Treaty with the Blackfoot, etc., 1868</ref></title> (Kappler, 1929, pp.
                    1138-1142).</note>
                <note id="n28">28. The transaction under consideration was the <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/tri0714.htm">
                        Treaty with the
                        Tribes of Middle Oregon, 1855</ref></title> (Kappler, 1904b, pp. 714-719).
                    See Bernholz and Weiner (2008b) for more on this instrument.</note>
                <note id="n29">29. Bernholz and Weiner (2008a) have identified Indian treaties that were
                    cited before the Courts of Claims.</note>
                <note id="n30">30. See examples of this use, reaching back to 1540, in <title>The Oxford
                        English Dictionary</title> (1989, vol. 19, p. 718).</note>
                <note id="n31">31. These seven documents &#8212; and their <title>Statutes at
                        Large</title> titles &#8212; are the <title>Treaty with the Choctaws and
                        Chickasaws</title> (11 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 573); the
                        <title>Treaty with the Choctaws and Chickasaws</title> (11 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 611); the <title>Treaty with the Chippewas</title> (11 <title
                        level="m">Stat.</title> 633); the <title>Treaty with Creeks and
                        Seminoles</title> (11 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 699); the <title>Treaty
                        with the Pawnees</title> (11 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 729); the
                        <title>Treaty with the Seneca Indians</title> (11 <title level="m"
                        >Stat.</title> 735); and the <title>Treaty with Yancton Tribe of
                        Sioux</title> (11 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 743).</note>
                <note id="n32">32. Some of the tribes had very old names &#8212; in part because
                    some groups were seen and named for the very first time at the turn of the
                    nineteenth century by Lewis and Clark and such designations endured; see the
                    names in the "Tribes of Indians" table in the <title>American State
                        Papers</title> (1832, p. lxxvii) for additional examples of old &#8212;
                    and now, in some cases, dispersed &#8212; groups. Those tribes "discovered"
                    by the Corps of Discovery were thought to include the Flathead ("Along the way
                    they met the Flathead Indians, another tribe who had never seen white men"
                    [Moulton, 1988, p. 3], and "The first non-Indians to make their way into
                    Flathead and Pend d'Oreille territory, and to record their journey, were members
                    of the Meriwether Lewis and William Clark expedition in 1805" [Malouf, 1998, p.
                    305]), and the Nez Perce (Walker, 1998). The Flathead and the Nez Perce have
                    tribal legends about these initial contacts with expedition members (Clark,
                    1966, pp. 129-131 and 57-60, respectively). Relevant to <title>Fort
                        Laramie</title>, the terms <title>Dar-co-tar</title> and
                        <title>Darcotar</title> initially appeared in the report by Lewis and Clark,
                    Estimate of the eastern Indians (Moulton, 1987a, pp. 386-450), and thereafter in
                    President Thomas Jefferson's communication to Congress in February 1806 of the
                    same materials under the title A statistical view of the Indian nations
                    inhabiting the territory of Louisiana and the countries adjacent to its northern
                    and western boundaries (1832). See Bright (2004) for other Indian tribe and
                    place names, and Criswell (1940, pp. xlvi-lx) for observations on Indians
                    identified by Lewis and Clark.</note>
                <note id="n33">33. Mary Eastman, in her "Preliminary remarks on the customs of the
                    Dahcotahs," confirmed "Dahcotah is the proper name of this once powerful tribe
                    of Indians. The term Sioux is not recognized, except among those who live near
                    the whites," and that "Dahcotah means a confederacy" (1849, p. xviii).</note>
                <note id="n34">34. The exclusion from <title>Laramie73</title>,
                    <title>Laramie03</title>, <title>Laramie04</title>, and <title>Laramie29</title>
                    of the Gros Ventre, Mandan, and Arikara subsection of Article 5 found in the
                    1851 transaction is misleading. The original treaty reads: ". . .thence up the
                    Yellow Stone river to the mouth of Powder River; <emph>thence from the mouth of
                        Powder River</emph> in a South-easterly direction to the head waters of the
                    Little Missouri river. . .," where the seven italicized words disappear from
                    those four later accounts. Kappler, for example, presents in his second edition
                    of <title>Indian Affairs</title>: ". . .thence up the Yellowstone River to the
                    mouth of Powder River in a southeasterly direction, to the head-waters of the
                    Little Missouri River. . ." (1904b, p. 594). A difficulty arises because a water
                    passage between the mouth of the Powder River and the headwaters of the Little
                    Missouri River is not possible (Stephan Custer and William Wyckoff, personal
                    communications, 14 October 2009). Further, the fact that the path "up the
                    Yellowstone River to the mouth of Powder River" progresses in a
                        south<emph>westerly</emph> direction that then requires a 90 turn to the
                    southeast to reorient to the direction of the Little Missouri. The
                        <title>Laramie51</title> thus provided useful data when it indicated that
                    the latter path should appropriately start "from the mouth of the Powder River;"
                    thereby noting that the Yellowstone segment had ended.</note>
                <note id="n35">35. Hill (1974, p. 213), in his presentation on the Office of Indian
                    Affairs, acknowledged that "The Yankton Agency (often spelled "Yancton") was
                    established in 1859 for the Yankton Sioux," so both spellings had appeared in
                    official correspondence prior to 1873. Kappler used the preferred 1900 "Names of
                    Indian tribes and bands" <title>Yankton</title> representation.</note>
                <note id="n36">36. Henry Ossum was a participant in the <title><ref
                        n="http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/Vol2/treaties/pot0367.htm">
                        Treaty with the
                        Pottawatomi, 1832</ref></title> (Kappler, 1904b, pp. 367-370).
                    He received $900 out of the $62,412 set aside for claims against the tribe in
                    Article 4 of that instrument. He appeared on the claims list in the <title>Statutes at
                    Large</title> (7 <title level="m">Stat.</title> 394, 396).</note>
                <note id="n37">37. Article identification and numbering varied in the versions of
                        <title>Fort Laramie</title>. Aust remarked that, in the drafting of such
                    instruments, "[i]n the past it was customary to use Roman numerals for articles.
                    . ." but that "[t]hey should be avoided like the plague, especially if the
                    treaty has many articles" (p. 429). The eight brief subsections in this contract
                    avoided the difficulties that Aust postulated in documents with many more text
                    components.</note>
                <note id="n38">38. Many of the accepted tribe spellings at the time of <title>Fort
                        Laramie</title> had been published more than half a century earlier in the
                    same <title>American State Papers</title> volume (1832, p. lxxvii), within a
                    table devoted to "Tribes of Indians" that had the directive "[f]or treaties or
                    proceedings with, or accounts of any particular tribe, see that tribe, under its
                    appropriate letter." The entry here for the "Flat Heads" would thus redirect
                    readers to <title>American State Papers: Indian Affairs</title> document number
                    113 &#8212; "Lewis and Clarke's Expedition" &#8212; for the "Flat Heads,
                    in 1805 &#8212; Statistical account by Lewis and Clarke of the," (p. 720).
                    Clark's misspelled name was also used in the 19 February 1806 communication to
                    Congress by President Jefferson (p. 705), and again in a subsequent extract from
                    a letter on 7 April 1805 by Meriwether Lewis to the President, in which Lewis
                    declared: "My inestimable friend and companion, Captain Clarke, has also enjoyed
                    good health generally" (p. 707). An examination for the same date in the
                        <title>Journals of the Lewis &amp; Clark Expedition</title> (Moulton,
                    1987b, p. 9) has Lewis writing a number of statements that involved Clark,
                    including the statement that "At same moment that the Barge departed from Fort
                    Mandan, Capt. Clark embaked with our party and proceeded up the river." Albert
                    Gallatin's significant <title>A Synopsis of the Indian Tribes</title> (1836)
                    spoke of the observations of "Lewis and Clarke."</note>
                <note id="n39">39. "The treaty identified approximately 38.5 million acres as Crow
                    territory" alone (<title>Montana v. United States</title>, 1981, p. 548), and
                    Hafen and Young (1938, p. 183) specified that "the Indian bands totaled more
                    than 10,000" at the gathering. At the time, the <title>North American and United
                        States Gazette</title> claimed that the event entailed "about twelve
                    thousand" Indians (Great Indian Council on the Plains, 1851, p. 1).</note>


            </div1>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
